<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Too Much Free Time</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/</id><updated>2015-07-01T19:08:25-04:00</updated><entry><title>Classic Nintendo Games are (NP-)Hard by Aloupis et al.</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/commentary/classic-nintendo-games-are-np-hard-by-aloupis-et-al.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-21T00:08:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-06-20:too-much-free-time/commentary/classic-nintendo-games-are-np-hard-by-aloupis-et-al.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting paper on arXiv, "Classic Nintendo Games are (NP-)Hard" by Greg Aloupis, Erik D. Demaine, Alan Guo, and Giovanni Viglietta. The paper is originally from 2012, but it's been updated in February of this year with additional results. It's been mentioned a few times on the web, but I didn't see anyone give a satisfactory explanation of what the paper is really about. I'm not an expert, but I'll give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, though, the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We prove NP-hardness results for five of Nintendo's largest video game franchises: Mario, Donkey Kong, Legend of Zelda, Metroid, and Pokemon. Our results apply to Super Mario Bros. 1, 3, Lost Levels, and Super Mario World; Donkey Kong Country 1-3; all Legend of Zelda games except Zelda II: The Adventure of Link; all Metroid games; and all Pokemon role-playing games. For Mario and Donkey Kong, we show NP-completeness. In addition, we observe that several games in the Zelda series are PSPACE-complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does it all mean?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll go into some detail shortly, but I'd like to describe in broad strokes what this is (and isn't).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors look at how hard it is to answer the question: given a particular level layout, a starting point, and a finish point, is it possible to get from the start to the finish?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't about the levels actually in the games--in fact, it isn't really about the level design &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. What it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; about is the rules of the games. &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;, for example, has several well-known rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mushrooms make small Mario big.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touching enemies (or some other hazards) makes big Mario small, or kills small Mario.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mario can break bricks only if he's big.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stars make Mario temporarily invulnerable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mario can jump to a height of 4 tiles, or 5 when running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more rules, but you see the point. Importantly, the authors specify that their results are about an &lt;em&gt;idealized&lt;/em&gt; version of the rules. In other words, glitches don't count. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the authors prove is that if you turn someone loose with a level editor, they can design a level for which it is very hard to determine whether it's even possible to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do this by showing that you can implement a problem called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_satisfiability_problem#3-satisfiability"&gt;3-satisfiability problem&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;3-SAT&lt;/em&gt;) in each of the games. Think of someone &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3FoNJeYY-Oc"&gt;using redstone to make &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Minecraft&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and you've got the general idea. 3-SAT is known to be NP-complete (read as: difficult), and the game it's implemented in must be &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; as hard as 3-SAT. Those problems are called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-hard"&gt;NP-hard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3-satisfiability problem is to determine if, given a boolean formula of a certain form, it is possible to set the variables (which can be either true or false) in such a way that the whole formula comes out true. A two-variable example of 3-SAT might be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;(y is TRUE | x is TRUE | x is TRUE)
    AND
(x is FALSE | y is TRUE | y is TRUE)
    AND
(x is FALSE | y is FALSE | y is FALSE)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Don't be alarmed by the duplication. The reason for writing that way will be apparent later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt; in 3-SAT means that each clause (the parts in parentheses) can have at most 3 components. In this case, each has only two &lt;em&gt;distinct&lt;/em&gt; components--one is repeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three clauses must be true for the formula to be true, and a clause is true if &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of its components (which are separated by pipes) is true. In logic-speak, it's a conjunction of several disjunctions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's pretty easy to see that this expression is true if y is true (satisfying the first part) and x is false (satisfying the other two). But what if there were fifty or a hundred or a billion sub-expressions? That would be harder to tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements for 3-SAT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be able to implement 3-SAT, you need a few components. You need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A starting point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A finishing point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to pick whether a variable is true or false&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way for those choices to either impede or allow progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to let paths cross without being able to change from one path to another&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last one is so that you can build big, complex paths. Without it, you'd be able to backtrack and mess things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors implement these components in 'gadgets', which are basically self-contained rooms or screens that can be connected to each other. They're the building blocks of the satisfiability puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gadgets in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll take a brief look at how the authors build these gadgets for &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;, as an example. This is going to be pretty much the same as what the authors say in the paper, so if you're feeling industrious, you can look at the paper and see how they put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Start&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start gadget is just where Mario starts the level--there's nothing to it. In general, the authors want Mario to be big throughout the level, so they put a mushroom at the beginning that will be required at the finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finish&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is trivial. It's just the flagpole. To make sure Mario stayed big throughout the level, you have him enter the screen with the flagpole in a corridor with a brick he must break to reach the flagpole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Finish gadget" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/aloupis2012-mario1-finish-gadget.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Variable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To pick whether a variable is true or false, Mario is given a screen with two possible paths--a vertical drop to either the left or right. Say left means "x is true" and right means "x is false". It doesn't matter which. The drops are long enough that Mario can't get back up, so once a choice is made, Mario can't go back and also take the other path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Clause and Check&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the most interesting (and important) gadget in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt; Take a look at it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Clause and Check gadget" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/aloupis2012-mario1-clause-gadget.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After making a choice and dropping from the Variable gadget, Mario will be led to a series of Clause gadgets. He enters one of the small open areas from the bottom--each one of them will have a path from a Variable gadget that leads to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each block contains a star, which will be trapped in the 'fence' when Mario hits the block. Later, Mario will come through the top part (that's the Check part of the gadget) and collect the star so that he can run through the Firebars. If Mario gets to the Check gadget without having hit the star block (thus satisfying the disjunction), he can't proceed--the Firebars will kill him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember our example of 3-SAT from earlier?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;(y is TRUE | x is TRUE | x is TRUE)
    AND
(x is FALSE | y is TRUE | y is TRUE)
    AND
(x is FALSE | y is FALSE | y is FALSE)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Imagine that the gadget pictured corresponds to the top disjunction, &lt;code&gt;(y is TRUE | x is TRUE | x is TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;. Then Mario will reach the left star block if he picked "y is TRUE" by dropping down the left side of the corresponding Variable gadget, and the middle and right star blocks by picking "x is TRUE" by dropping down the left side of &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; particular Variable gadget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if Mario picked "x is false" and "y is false"? Then he'd never get to the blocks and release the star, so when he got to the Check gadget, the Firebars would kill him. That means that both variables being false isn't a solution to the expression, and (equivalently) taking the right path at both variable gadgets won't let Mario finish the level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crossover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just a utility to let paths cross without Mario backtracking and making two different choices for one Variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Crossover gadget" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/aloupis2012-mario1-crossover-gadget.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mario comes in from the lower path, he can break the bricks and keep going up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If he comes in from the upper path, he can run into the Goomba to become small, head to the right, pick up the mushroom from the block, break the brick, and continue to the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small Mario can't break the bricks in the middle to go up, and big Mario can't get through the narrow paths to go to the right. Big Mario also can't break the bricks and then go back, because the drop on the left is too far for him to get back up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Putting it all together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can string together as many Variable, Clause, and Check gadgets as you need to make as big of a problem as you want. Since we know that 3-SAT is NP-complete, and we've just implemented 3-SAT in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;, we know that &lt;em&gt;SMB&lt;/em&gt; is NP-hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! If you've made it this far, then you've got the major idea of (part of) the paper. Pick up your CS degree on the way out the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other games, other problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't go into detail about the other sections of the paper, but if you've read this far, you should be able to read the paper and see what is being done. The proofs for other Mario games just make some modifications to the gadgets we looked at above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proofs for the Zelda games are different. They still work by implementing an NP-hard problem, but it's a different problem, and they implement it using the sliding blocks in the Zelda series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to know about the other games, or get more details, take look at the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Caveat lector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done my best, here, but I'm not an expert. I've got a BS in math, not a doctorate in computer science. If I've made some terrible mistake, it's all my fault (and I'd appreciate it if you'd let me know!), and I apologize for anything misleading, confusing, or dangerous that I've written. Always wear proper safety equipment when proving theorems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Aloupis2012v3]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Greg Aloupis &amp;amp; Erik D. Demaine &amp;amp; Alan Guo et al., &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1203.1895v3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Classic Nintendo Games are (NP-)Hard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,  (2012-03-08).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;</summary><category term="academic"></category><category term="computational complexity"></category><category term="Mario"></category><category term="Donkey Kong"></category><category term="Zelda"></category><category term="Metroid"></category><category term="Pokemon"></category></entry><entry><title>TIS-100</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/tis-100.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T12:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-06-19:too-much-free-time/game/tis-100.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="TIS-100 opening screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/370360_2015-06-17_00004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I saw a new game from &lt;a href="http://www.zachtronics.com/"&gt;Zachtronics Industries&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;, which was released &lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/370360/"&gt;on Steam&lt;/a&gt; as an early access title on the first of June. In some ways, calling it a game is overstating it: it's little more than a collection of programming problems, with a little story to give it some structure. The catch is that you're programming in an assembly language on a virtual machine with unusual architecture; problems beyond the simplest will generally require you to take advantage of parallelism (which is the primary distinguishing feature of the VM), resulting in novel solutions for ordinary problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="TIS-100 game screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/370360_2015-06-17_00005.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, a game like that has a rather limited target audience. Case in point: I have myself previously created a little VM with a fake assembly language to play with. The game is clearly made just for me, but how many others are likely to be similarly interested? About 11,000,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; so far. It's a minor hit.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of programming as gameplay isn't new. Indeed, Zachtronics's earlier game, &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;, is also an exercise in parallel programming, though dressed up in fancier clothes. Way back in the mists of time,&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;Robot Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; challenged players to program the titular robots to solve puzzles. And on the more-programming-than-game end of the spectrum, we have &lt;em&gt;Core War&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a multitude of web sites in the vein of &lt;a href="https://projecteuler.net/"&gt;Project Euler&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.codingame.com/home"&gt;CodinGame&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been enjoying &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;, but more than that, I think it's singularly impressive to release a game of this kind. Certainly, there are games that trade on their difficulty (&lt;em&gt;Super Hexagon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;I Wanna Be the Guy&lt;/em&gt;, etc.) and some that take pride in their difficulty of interaction (&lt;em&gt;Surgeon Simulator&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ampu-Tea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;QWOP&lt;/em&gt;, etc.), and simple 'retro-style' graphics are &lt;em&gt;de rigueur&lt;/em&gt; for indie games, but the very minimalistic functionalism of &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; is astounding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; is difficult because the thinking required to solve the puzzles is difficult. It is perhaps inaccessible, because it consists of nothing else &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the tools to solve the puzzle. Its graphics are simple because everything you need to solve the puzzles is a text-mode interactive debugger, and that's what you get. Like a sudoku puzzle or a crossword, &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; is a completely pure puzzle game: the game takes place in your head, and the software keeps score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not by chance that &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; so distinguishes itself from other games. During the production of &lt;em&gt;Infinifactory&lt;/em&gt;, Zach Barth, the founder of Zachtronics, wanted to make a game with a smaller team--something more-indie-than-indie--to get back to his roots as an indie developer. The project turned out to be too great in scope, but from its wreckage was salvaged a programming minigame which became &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Viewed as an indie developer's attempt to make something &lt;em&gt;even more indie&lt;/em&gt;, with the understanding that it was a small part of something larger, the design makes sense.&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game's manual, too, reflects the niche targeted by the game. Who reads a manual, you ask? When it is positioned as a technical document describing the instruction set of a virtual machine, the answer to that question is: programmers. The manual is presented as the in-universe manual for the TIS-100 computer, previously the property of the player character's Uncle Randy, including handwritten notes and highlighting. This was part of Zachtronics's attempt to make a game with "an irresistible value proposition. For us, that's a game with a 14-page technical manual that we designed, printed out, marked up and scanned back in again."&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:7" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The manual is reminiscent of the feelies accompanying Infocom games, among others, in years past.&lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:8" rel="footnote"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="TIS-100 results screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/370360_2015-06-18_00001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like its predecessor, &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; encourages players to perfect their solutions, optimizing for either execution speed, least number of nodes used, or least instructions--goals which are often contradictory, requiring multiple solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps unsurprisingly, given that it is a game about programming, the players of &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; have created some auxiliary tools, including &lt;a href="http://www.tis100pad.com/"&gt;TIS-100 PAD&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;sup id="fnref:9"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:9" rel="footnote"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which allows users to more easily share solutions, and a variety of TIS-100 (the virtual machine, not the game) emulators.&lt;sup id="fnref:10"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:10" rel="footnote"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this unsolicited community participation, with the release of the specification editor, which allows players to make their own puzzles, a puzzle design contest was announced. Twenty-five puzzles will be selected from the submissions for an official bonus campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feel of &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; is both nostalgic and quite modern. It's an intriguing combination, and I recommend it to anyone still interested after hearing me call it "a collection of programming problems." Coders, no prior experience with assembly is needed. Others, if you like this game--try coding. You'll probably like that, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Barth2012]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Zach Barth, &lt;a href="http://gamasutra.com/view/feature/172250/postmortem_zachtronics_.php"&gt;Postmortem: Zachtronics Industries' &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Gamasutra (2012-06-13).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Dewdney1984]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Alexander K. Dewdney, &lt;a href="http://www.koth.org/info/akdewdney/First.htm"&gt;In the game called Core War hostile programs engage in a battle of bits&lt;/a&gt;, Scientific American &lt;strong&gt;250&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt; (1984), 15--19.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[McIlroy1971]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;M. Douglas McIlroy &amp;amp; Robert Morris &amp;amp; Victor Vyssotsky, &lt;a href="http://www.cs.dartmouth.edu/~doug/darwin.pdf"&gt;Letter to Aleph-Null&lt;/a&gt; (1971-06-29).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Wawro2015]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Alex Wawro, &lt;a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/244969/Things_we_create_tell_people_who_we_are_Designing_Zachtronics_TIS100.php"&gt;'Things we create tell people who we are': Designing Zachtronics' &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Gamasutra (2015-06-09).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://steamspy.com/app/370360"&gt;According to SteamSpy&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, it has 270 positive reviews and 2 negative reviews &lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/370360/"&gt;on Steam&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1984, actually. It was released a year later for DOS, &lt;a href="http://www.mobygames.com/game/robot-odyssey/release-info"&gt;according to MobyGames&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also from 1984, described in a Scientific American article, [Dewdney1984]. It's based on a still earlier programming game, &lt;em&gt;Darwin&lt;/em&gt;, which was played in 1961 and described publicly in 1972. See [McIlroy1971] for more.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The details of &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;'s inception, and more, are discussed in an interview published by Gamasutra, [Wawro2015].&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Barth wrote in a post mortem of &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;, [Barth2012], that &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt; was too difficult and inaccessible. New titles were forthcoming: "New titles, I might add, that are hopefully more accessible than &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;!"&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From [Wawro2015].&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when you &lt;em&gt;got something&lt;/em&gt; for your money! &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/commentary/software-in-the-age-of-sneakernet-a-pictorial.html"&gt;Even application software used to have much more bulk to it&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:8" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source available &lt;a href="https://github.com/Triplanetary/tis100pad"&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:9" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just have a look at the results of &lt;a href="https://github.com/search?p=2&amp;amp;amp;q=tis-100&amp;amp;amp;type=Repositories&amp;amp;amp;utf8=%E2%9C%93"&gt;this search&lt;/a&gt;. But watch out, if you'd like to avoid spoilers! The puzzle solutions are code, after all, so a number of people have posted those, as well.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:10" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="programming game"></category><category term="Zachtronics Industries"></category><category term="puzzle"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="Windows"></category><category term="2015"></category></entry><entry><title>Bleed Out Sakuretsu</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/bleed-out-sakuretsu.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T12:53:04-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-04-05:too-much-free-time/game/bleed-out-sakuretsu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don't believe I've written about any remotely popular games for at least two years... and I'm not about to change that. But I am writing about a good game, at least: &lt;em&gt;Bleed Out Sakuretsu&lt;/em&gt;, a vertically scrolling shooter for the Sharp X68000, by Gold Cats Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bleed Out Sakuretsu title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Bleed-Out-Sakuretsu-title.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First: yes, the title screen says 'sakuretu'. But the common romanization of this game's title seems to be 'sakuretsu', and as goes TOSEC, so goes my nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="In-game" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Bleed-Out-Sakuretsu-ingame.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bleed Out Sakuretsu&lt;/em&gt; has a powerup system reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;Gradius&lt;/em&gt;. As you continue scoring points, you can purchase a shot upgrade, a barrier, or other, even more powerful powerups. The opposition is a variety of ships, small shots, and guided missiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Boss fight" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Bleed-Out-Sakuretsu-boss.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boss sprays out bullets danmaku-style, and periodically fires a pair of front-facing lasers. You've got to deal with this while avoiding guided missiles, and since you are destroyed in one shot (unless you buy a barrier), this, like the rest of the level, provides a good challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, an unfortunate revelation: the boss is, as far as I can tell, invulnerable, because the available version of &lt;em&gt;Bleed Out Sakuretsu&lt;/em&gt; is a trial edition, and I can find no evidence that any full version was ever created. I would love to hear otherwise, if anyone has better information on old doujin games than I do, because it's a very fun game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qMZdr6LtHT8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to do a shooter justice with just words and screenshots. The video above shows (I believe) the entire game, which should give a much better picture of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like shooters, I'd say &lt;em&gt;Bleed Out Sakuretsu&lt;/em&gt; is worth a try. It's only about two minutes long, but it's fun, and I believe there's a place for brief games, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Touhou&lt;/em&gt; series looms largest on the doujin shooter landscape, of course, but there's a huge and fascinating variety of games (of all genres) stretching back decades, which I think could use some more attention from the English-speaking web. I'll probably be looking at a few more doujin games in coming weeks, so I'll try to shine a light on whichever titles catch my eye. Maybe there will be some hidden gems, or maybe just hidden failures. We'll see what comes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="doujin shooter"></category><category term="Gold Cats Project"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="vaporware"></category><category term="1996"></category><category term="x68000"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="good"></category></entry><entry><title>History Mystery</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/history-mystery.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T13:47:29-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-03-12:too-much-free-time/game/history-mystery.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the early eighties, the sudden popularity (and, indeed, the recent &lt;em&gt;existence&lt;/em&gt;) of home computers gave rise to a new kind of publication: the disk magazine. These periodicals were published not on paper but on computer disks (and sometimes cassettes), and although the content varied, they generally featured computer programs (including games) in addition to, or even in place of, articles. The most famous of these are perhaps &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Softdisk_(disk_magazine)"&gt;Softdisk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; for the Apple II (launched in 1981) and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loadstar"&gt;Loadstar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; for the Commodore 64 (launched in 1984). The medium flourished&lt;sup id="fnref:diskmags"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:diskmags" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; alongside more traditional magazines which might offer (inconvenient!) type-in programs. There was a price to be paid for this convenience: a single 'issue' of &lt;em&gt;Softdisk&lt;/em&gt; cost about the same as an annual subscription to a paper magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the many disk mags was Scholastic's &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; for Apple II. Featuring (as you might expect) primarily educational content, &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; began publication in 1983,&lt;sup id="fnref:micropub"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:micropub" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; continuing for about a decade. It also inspired a spin-off series, &lt;em&gt;Microzine Jr.&lt;/em&gt;, which was launched in 1988. Each issue of &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; included four programs, one of which was a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="History Mystery title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Microzine18.Sid_000000004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which all brings me to the subject of this article: &lt;em&gt;History Mystery&lt;/em&gt; by David A. Bowman and &lt;a href="http://www.highcastle.com/MarkHome/mark.htm"&gt;Mark A. Malamud&lt;/a&gt;, which was included in &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; #18 in November 1986. According to the '&lt;a href="https://tmft.wordpress.com/?attachment_id=945"&gt;Letter from the Editor&lt;/a&gt;' in that issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll have fun reading &lt;strong&gt;The History Mystery&lt;/strong&gt; Twistaplot™ adventure. A priceless hourglass has been stolen from the Microville History Museum. Some of the ghosts in the museum will help you find it. (Yes, the museum is haunted!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You play the part of "the ace reporter of your school newspaper, &lt;span style="text-decoration:underline;"&gt;The Chronicle&lt;/span&gt;" (incidentally, &lt;a href="https://tmft.wordpress.com/?attachment_id=953"&gt;of selectable gender&lt;/a&gt;), out to get a story about a stolen Babylonian hourglass. After chatting with the ghost of Mark Twain about the situation, you find yourself in the lobby of the museum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Museum lobby" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Microzine18.Sid_000000014.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The museum consists of 29 rooms&lt;sup id="fnref:map"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:map" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which you must navigate, gathering items and clues to solve the mystery of the stolen hourglass, which the museum's ghosts believe is actually located within the museum. Each room has a description, seen on entering the room, and an entry in the self-guided tape-recorded tour, accessed by pressing &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;. The tour often contained educational information&lt;sup id="fnref:tour"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:tour" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which might be used to solve the game's puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Age of Dinosaurs room" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Microzine18.Sid_000000019.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some rooms have items to be collected, while others have ghosts to talk to or other objects to interact with. The game is in two parts (purely for practical reasons, I presume). Selecting the second part from the menu requires the player to input the password given at the end of the first part ("The Sands of Time") and begins the second part, in which the player must collect the hourglass and escape the museum while being chased by Winsome Slugg, the criminal who had stolen it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tracy's Gift Shop" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tracys-gift-shop.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon completing the game, the player gets a rather neat reward: the museum's gift shop, called "Amy Minkley's Gift Shop",&lt;sup id="fnref:giftshop"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:giftshop" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; will be renamed after the player. Not only in the ending text, either: in future playthroughs, the in-game name is changed. Which, I suppose, might make this the first game with a New Game+ feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;History Mystery&lt;/em&gt; took me about an hour to complete, though I suppose it took me quite a bit longer when I was a child. I remember having a lot of fun with it, back then, and it's still neat as a bit of nostalgia, today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tales of Suspense" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tales-of-suspense.jpg" /&gt;
My copy of the game is this 1987 compilation, &lt;em&gt;Tales of Suspense&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll try to look at some more games from &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; and other disk mags in the future. There's a lot to be said about them, and the resources on the internet are scarce at best. This post has been several years in the making, during which time I've been contacted a number of times by people who, like me, had fond memories of a game which &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; have been &lt;em&gt;History Mystery&lt;/em&gt;, but who couldn't be sure. My thanks to them for providing me the impetus to do my civic duty and get this out there. Fans of old educational games, you are appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:diskmags"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia has &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_disk_magazines"&gt;a substantial list&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:diskmags" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:micropub"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="http://apple2history.org/history/ah21/#15"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: "The first issue of &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; was first displayed at the January 1983 Consumer Electronics Show, and was available in stores by March 1983.")&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:micropub" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:map"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mapped them out &lt;a href="https://tmft.wordpress.com/?attachment_id=947"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:map" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:tour"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"...Welcome to the Telephone Exhibit. The first telephone call was made by Alexander Graham Bell. As he was calling, he accidently spilled acid on himself and yelled for his assistant: 'Mr. Watson, come here. I want you!'...."&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:tour" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:giftshop"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the game, "named after one of the great school reporters" (probably the editor of your school newspaper, Amy Minkly), but likely &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; named after Amy E. McKinley, the editor of &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt;--though perhaps she was a school reporter, once.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:giftshop" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="history"></category><category term="David A. Bowman"></category><category term="Mark A. Malamud"></category><category term="Microzine"></category><category term="new game plus"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="Scholastic"></category><category term="selectable gender"></category><category term="educational"></category><category term="1986"></category><category term="adventure"></category><category term="Apple II"></category><category term="good"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on Ferguson's Media Violence Paper</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/commentary/thoughts-on-fergusons-media-violence-paper.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-11-09:too-much-free-time/commentary/thoughts-on-fergusons-media-violence-paper.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My attention was directed to &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jcom.12129/full"&gt;a paper by Christopher J. Ferguson&lt;/a&gt;, to be published in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Communication&lt;/em&gt;, which argues that the common belief that there is a positive correlation between media violence and societal violence is false. The abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article presents 2 studies of the association of media violence rates with societal violence rates. In the first study, movie violence and homicide rates are examined across the 20th century and into the 21st (1920–2005). Throughout the mid-20th century small-to-moderate correlational relationships can be observed between movie violence and homicide rates in the United States. This trend reversed in the early and latter 20th century, with movie violence rates inversely related to homicide rates. In the second study, videogame violence consumption is examined against youth violence rates in the previous 2 decades. Videogame consumption is associated with a decline in youth violence rates. Results suggest that societal consumption of media violence is not predictive of increased societal violence rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The article, briefly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the full article is about twenty pages, I'll summarize it here, with a bit more detail than the abstract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ferguson begins by establishing that there is not general agreement in the literature as to correlation (much less causation) between media violence and societal violence. He particularly argues that that laboratory studies which show an increase in aggression (e.g. an increased tendency to fill in missing letters in words to create violent words) following consumption of violent media may not correspond to increased societal violence (e.g. homicide).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first study analyzes the relationship between violence in movies and homicide, between 1920 and 2005. To assess violence in movies, the top five grossing movies per year were taken at five-year intervals, and graded for violent content. This data was compared to statistics for murder and (non-negligent) homicide during the same years. Ferguson concludes that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together these data suggest that perceived correlations between movie and societal violence were associated with a chance concordance during the mid-20th century. Given that these phenomena were not in concordance in either the early or latter 20th century, it appears that efforts to establish causal connections between movie and societal violence based on a select set of decades were an ecological fallacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second study analyzes the relationship between violence in video games and youth violence for the years 1996 to 2011. Ferguson uses sales data from IMDb and the ESA and takes the ratings assigned by the ESRB as a proxy for violent content. He concludes that there is a "remarkably strong" inverse relationship between violent video game consumption and youth violence and that, although this is no indication of causality, "Evidence from societal data does not support claims of dramatic videogame violence effects on violence among youth."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Ferguson argues that alternate methods should be used in the future when assessing the effect of media consumption on behavior, and that professional organizations such as the APA should "retire their policy statements on media violence as such statements tend to be misleading and may cause more harm than good." Furthermore, "Arguably, given that the results from the effects paradigm have been weak and inconsistent, it may be time for scholars to make less rather than more conclusive statements to news media regarding media effects on society."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unaddressed questions and other problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ferguson's conclusion in the first study (namely that positive correlation between media violence and societal violence is limited to a mid-century concordance) seems undeniable. I am not similarly satisfied with the second study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious problem with the second study is that it addresses a period of only sixteen years, and in particular that it does not even consider whether the change in rate of youth violence differed before and after the introduction of video games. Given that Ferguson strongly criticized reliance on data from a limited time span in the first study, this is fairly damning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the second study does not argue that &lt;em&gt;generally&lt;/em&gt; increased video game consumption corresponds to an increase in the consumption of &lt;em&gt;violent&lt;/em&gt; video games &lt;em&gt;by youths&lt;/em&gt;. I freely admit that it is likely that this is true, but the study makes no mention of it. In general, I am not convinced by Ferguson's 'just look at the top five games according to IMDb' approach to analyzing the state of gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the study blithely dismisses any correlation between increased incarceration and decreased youth violence, on strength of &lt;a href="http://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ875143"&gt;a paper by Stahlkopf, Males, and Macallair&lt;/a&gt;. Based on its abstract, that paper only concludes that increased &lt;em&gt;juvenile&lt;/em&gt; incarceration does not lead to reduced crime (specifically in California). It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible that the full paper has more useful (for Ferguson) conclusions, but I do not have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourth, the graphs in the paper are unclear as to what exactly is depicted. Figure 3, "Societal videogame violence consumption and societal youth violence, 1996-2011.", is a double chart with yearly figures for the two measures in question, with scales ranging from 0-9000 for one and 0-40 for the other. 9000 what? 40 what? I have no idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifth, without commenting on the sensibility of the suggestions Ferguson makes, I would say that his statements in the "Theoretical implications" section are not supported by the studies. Ferguson argues that different theoretical approaches should be used in studying the relationship between media violence and societal violence, essentially by mentioning a variety of alternatives without arguing for their particular effectiveness. Such arguments would be better suited to a paper which actually considers the relative merit of the various approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sixth, the "Policy implications" section reads like a conspiracy theory. Selections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a matter of policy, consistent with the statement by the Consortium of Scholars (2013)...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...media-based policy statements released by professional organizations have so often been revealed to be flawed (e.g., Ferguson, 2013;Magid, 2011).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...it has been revealed that past policy statements were typically
developed by specially selected researchers heavily invested in antimedia views, with no dissenting voices (Ferguson, 2013).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, problems have been 'revealed' &lt;em&gt;by the author of this paper&lt;/em&gt;. The 'statement by the Consortium of Scholars' mentioned is an open letter of which Ferguson is a signatory, and the source of which is &lt;em&gt;Ferguson's personal website&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:homepage"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:homepage" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reference to Magid links to a paper published in &lt;em&gt;Pediatrics&lt;/em&gt; (by O'Keeffe and Clarke-Pearson), but the actual reference listed is to an article in &lt;em&gt;Huffington Post&lt;/em&gt; which responds to (and disputes) the journal article. Why Ferguson would obfuscatingly link to the article in &lt;em&gt;Pediatrics&lt;/em&gt; rather than the one in &lt;em&gt;HuffPo&lt;/em&gt; to which he actually referred is a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, take note of "...some scholars have argued...(Males, 2013)." That reference is not to a scholarly paper, but what seems to be simply an opinion piece published by YouthFacts.org.&lt;sup id="fnref:broken"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:broken" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the actual studies in the paper seem fairly inoffensive, but do not support the discussion. It seems very like Ferguson wanted to pontificate about perceived problems in his field, and conducted a couple of very minor studies in order to have an excuse for publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I have not studied psychology. I studied math at uni, so except insofar as the paper uses statistical analyses, I have no formal education relevant to this paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, as I do not have access to a university library, I have not been able to review all of the paper's references. It is possible that some or all of my objections were answered by the cited papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, I am (obviously) a gamer, and inclined to agree with the &lt;em&gt;results&lt;/em&gt; of the studies in this paper, despite my objections to the academic rigour of the paper. It is possible that I have been too lenient with the studies for this reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Ferguson2015]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Christopher J. Ferguson, &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jcom.12129/full"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does Media Violence Predict Societal Violence? It Depends on What You Look at and When&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Journal of Communication &lt;strong&gt;65&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; (2015), E1--E22.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Magid2011]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Larry Magid, &lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/larry-magid/facebook-depression-nonexistent_b_842733.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Facebook Depression': A Nonexistent Condition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, The Huffington Post (2011-03-30).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[OKeeffe2011]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gwenn Schurgin O'Keeffe &amp;amp; Kathleen Clarke-Pearson &amp;amp; Council on Communications and Media, &lt;a href="http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/127/4/800.full"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The impact of social media on children, adolescents, and families&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Pediatrics &lt;strong&gt;127&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; (2011), 800--804.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Stahlkopf2010]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Christina Stahlkopf &amp;amp; Mike Males &amp;amp; Daniel Macallair, &lt;a href="http://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ875143"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Testing Incapacitation Theory Youth Crime and Incarceration in California&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Crime &amp;amp; Delinquency &lt;strong&gt;56&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; (2010), 253--268.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:homepage"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which, incidentally, &lt;a href="http://www.christopherjferguson.com/"&gt;looks more like the geocities homepage of a teenager&lt;/a&gt; than the website of a professional academic.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:homepage" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:broken"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a broken link, besides--&lt;a href="http://youthfacts.org/files/articles/bloomberg_guns2_06012013.html"&gt;here's a working one&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:broken" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="academic"></category><category term="Christopher J. Ferguson"></category><category term="violence"></category></entry><entry><title>IFComp 2014: One Night Stand</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-one-night-stand.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:32:51-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-10-19:too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-one-night-stand.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The third game I've played from the 2014 ifcomp is &lt;em&gt;One Night Stand&lt;/em&gt; by Giannis G. Georgiou. You play Sandy, a woman who is trying to discover the name of the man she just spent the night with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One pre-spoiler note: the download from the comp website just has an HTML file with a link to a web-based version of the game, but the story file &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be downloaded, if you follow that link. You'll need a Quest interpreter to play it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This post contains spoilers. Read at your own risk.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a note about online play: the online interpreter was rather slow to react, occasionally taking many seconds to complete a command, and usually missing the first few characters of each command I typed, since it was still scrolling the response text. This was irritating, but it otherwise worked fine, and it was at least visually attractive. Not ideal, but better than nothing, given that I don't actually have a Quest interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ONS&lt;/em&gt; is a short comedy game with one puzzle sequence. I spent about 35 minutes prodding everything in the game before I finished, but I imagine 10 minutes would more than suffice, if you just proceed toward the goal--and particularly if you aren't using the rather slow web-based interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the customized responses to trying to take various objects, and the randomly chosen sections of text (e.g. when knocking on Mara's door) are a nice touch. The ending, though not &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; unexpected, is a good enough payoff for the few minutes the game takes to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, you don't have any real options--either you proceed linearly through the story, or you don't proceed at all. I wanted to try tricking the dude into saying his name. To break down in tears to avoid the situation. To call him Rumpelstiltskin, if his name is so important. Anything to have some choice--but I had none. More mundanely, there are few objects implemented, and no real, interactive NPCs. The parser is a little obtuse, too: you've got to &lt;strong&gt;knock door&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;use bottle on floor&lt;/strong&gt;, which aren't exactly the first commands that came to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, an average-quality game, which would probably be more at home in the first ifcomp than the twentieth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Post-review pre-posting note&lt;/em&gt;: Okay, I think this review needs an addendum. Other reviewers seem to be unanimous in despising this game. It was my assumption throughout the game that it was a work of parody--the several-inches deep layer of grease on the kitchen floor not a greater exaggeration than the PC's absurd internal monologue. &lt;em&gt;Surely&lt;/em&gt; the game is so stupid exactly because it's undermining its nominal position. Of course, while writing the review, I was under the impression that the author was a woman (Wrong! Giannis is a Greek name which is the masculine form Gianna. The more you know.), and that therefore the PC &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be a parody of the ridiculous caricatures of women we see in games and other media (maybe not?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's against my policy to change my judgment after reading other reviews, so I'll let this review stand as-is. I'd rather be too generous in my assumptions about other people than too harsh. In retrospect, though, if you take seriously the bits that I assumed to be failed comedy, then the game really &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; become rather unpalatable... so take this review with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="female protagonist"></category><category term="ifcomp 2014"></category><category term="2014"></category><category term="freeware"></category><category term="interactive fiction"></category><category term="platform independent"></category><category term="Giannis G. Georgiou"></category></entry><entry><title>IFComp 2014: Raik</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-raik.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:38:06-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-10-17:too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-raik.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The second game I'm looking at this year is &lt;em&gt;Raik&lt;/em&gt; by Harry Giles, which is written with Twine. According to the blurb, it is "A scots fantasia about anxiety. Battle kelpies, watch TV, avoid your emails and find the magical Staff of the Salmon." Sounds amusing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This post contains spoilers. Read at your own risk.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My spoiler warning above goes double for this game. Really definitely don't read this without playing the game. I mean it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start the game, you're advised that you can "Learn about Scots and use a translator at &lt;a href="http://www.scots-online.org/"&gt;Scots-Online.org&lt;/a&gt;", and you are presented with a pair of links: &lt;strong&gt;gang&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;go&lt;/strong&gt;. It looks from the outset as if the game is simply available in two languages--Scots and English--for flavor, and the "Translate to Scots" and "Translate to English" links that appear reinforce this. The text is even very similar in shape in each language. However, this is only a facade: there are two stories being told, and they are superficially unrelated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Scots-language story, the PC struggles through the day, trying to fill time: "If ye can get tae hauf five, mebbe ye can get tae dinner, than mebbe ye can get tae bed."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the English-language story, the PC is on an epic quest: "You are searching for the Staff of the Salmon, whose magic alone will release your clan from the withering curse of Black Edward."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the bottom of each page of text is an option to 'translate' into the other language, which actually presents not a translation but the section of the story which is in the corresponding position in the other language: the stories are structurally the same. They are related in more ways that one: at the end of the English-language story, "You imagine another version of yourself, who stayed in bed that fateful day and even now lies frozen in time, unable to act, an endless scream seeking only relief." In the most recent corresponding part of the Scots-language story, the PC is paralyzed by a panic attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interpretation: the Scots-language story is 'real', and the English-language story is the PC's way of dealing with life--or of &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; dealing with life, as the case may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The duality of the stories is very cool and well done. Though you could (mostly) play them separately, the English-language story serves as commentary on the Scots-language story. For example, when the PC of the Scots-language story is (figuratively) lost in a panic attack, the PC of the English-language story is (literally) lost in a maze. It's an impressive way to use metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The individual stories are well-crafted, too. I particularly liked the use of links to pace the story. Early on, links interrupting the text make the story seem to move slower, but later they make the pacing seem more frantic--well done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll note that my praise is all for 'meta' aspects of the game--this is not an accident. The &lt;em&gt;actual game&lt;/em&gt; isn't all that interesting. The Scots-language story is dull (but it's &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be, since it's the 'real-world' part of the game) and the English-language story is far from engaging. However, the game is quite short (about fifteen minutes for a single playthrough), so this wasn't a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language aspect could prove something of a problem. It's easy enough to tell the general sense of the Scots-language story, but for most readers there will be &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; specific terms that require definition. It's certainly the author's intention to induce readers to learn more about Scots, which is fine, though I wonder how much effort the (non-comp-judging) general public will be willing to expend on comprehension. My own experience with Scots (other than &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To_a_Mouse"&gt;Robert Burns&lt;/a&gt;) is limited to an encounter with the &lt;a href="https://sco.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page"&gt;Scots Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, some years ago. At the time, I judged that the editors were treating Scots as a somewhat more dignified version of leet-speak, and put it from my mind. It &lt;a href="https://stats.wikimedia.org/EN/SummarySCO.htm"&gt;seems to have done better since&lt;/a&gt;, though it still has very few editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the author, &lt;em&gt;Raik&lt;/em&gt; was inspired by &lt;em&gt;Depression Quest&lt;/em&gt;, which I have not yet played. I'd like to come back to this game after playing &lt;em&gt;Depression Quest&lt;/em&gt;, to see how it affects my opinion. At any rate, I foresee myself continuing to revisit and think about this game in the future, which is about the highest praise that can be given to a 'serious' game like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play time: about 40 minutes for several playthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="freeware"></category><category term="interactive fiction"></category><category term="platform independent"></category><category term="Harry Giles"></category><category term="ifcomp 2014"></category><category term="mental health"></category><category term="storytelling"></category><category term="2014"></category></entry><entry><title>IFComp 2014: Hill 160</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-hill-160.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:43:27-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-10-17:too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-hill-160.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new year brings a new ifcomp. The first game, this year, is &lt;em&gt;Hill 160&lt;/em&gt; by Mike Gerwat, billed as "A World War I Adventure in Terror". This appears to be Gerwat's first comp entry, though he has released another game, &lt;em&gt;Genesis Quest&lt;/em&gt;, which is available &lt;a href="http://www.ifarchive.org/if-archive/games/glulx/GenesisQuest.ulx"&gt;on the ifarchive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This post contains spoilers. Read at your own risk.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, this first game is one I couldn't finish. The author indicates that this game has been made easier to comply with the comp rules (the two-hour rule, I suppose), but I sincerely doubt that anyone will finish the game, because the walkthrough is a bit over 700 commands long. To complete the game you'd need to execute one (correct!) command every &lt;em&gt;ten seconds&lt;/em&gt;. Judging by the walkthrough, in 48 minutes I got through about a sixth of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the game were only too long, I would have continued to play for the full two hours games are allotted. Unfortunately, the game has three crippling flaws: first, it is tedious; second, it is unfriendly (more on this later); third, it is buggy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tedium is, I presume, intentional: it's intended to reflect the tedium of war. To that end, the game involves plenty of actions that are boring, repetitive, or both. The walkthrough contains (from about 700 turns) 57 turns of waiting, 19 turns of sleeping, and 16 turns of 'again', which are mostly sleeping or waiting. When you are acting, you are often doing something like &lt;strong&gt;drop pants / crap in trench / pull up pants&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unfriendliness is the main reason I gave up. Any little thing you do that isn't according to script will generally end the game. Leave the latrine without using it? "You didn't take your shite! GAME OVER MATEY!". Walk onto the battlefield without cleaning your rifle? "You didn't clean your rifle! GAME OVER MATEY!". Try to take the supplies you're after, rather than asking for them? "GAME OVER MATEY!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not generally obvious what you're meant to do until you've already failed. How was I to know I had to clean the rifle? It's description didn't mention anything. For that matter, how was I to know I had to attach the bayonet myself? The game over message tells me that "Your rifle is missing a critical part.", but attempting to examine it again gives me "You've already examined the rifle.". The game won't let you examine anything twice, or talk to anyone twice. If you don't have a transcript, you'd better have remembered the names of the members of your platoon--you won't be seeing them again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not always obvious how to accomplish things, either. When you're sent for supplies, trying to simply take them from the supply party gets you killed, but &lt;strong&gt;talk to party&lt;/strong&gt; gives "You can't talk to the supply party." In fact, you must &lt;strong&gt;ask party for supplies&lt;/strong&gt;. But &lt;strong&gt;talk to grant&lt;/strong&gt; worked, earlier. The requirements are inconsistent. Once, when talking to Grant, you must salute (or game over!), but later, saluting isn't necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the game is buggy. If you talk to Grant in the Main Trench before going out on the recon mission, he gives the speech that he gave earlier about you needing to go pick up supplies. Waiting repeatedly will repeatedly give the text about Grant arriving. Sometimes waiting will just do nothing with no message at all. And it's not strictly a bug, but &lt;strong&gt;take all&lt;/strong&gt; should not open up every container and fill my inventory with several screens worth of cigarettes and grenades and things. It should just pick up the items I dropped. Very irritating!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that said, the game does have its good points. The author indicates that it's intended to be fairly realistic, based on his over 40 years of study, and there are plenty of interesting details. There are some detailed descriptions of certain items, and the language and situation are (apparently--the first World War is not my forte) also intended to be realistic. For my part, I'd enjoy it more simply exploring the environment than having the game nag at me about every minor detail (and the author promises that "When it goes up on the archive, it will be much harder with Release 2." Not necessary!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hill 160&lt;/em&gt; has potential, but I won't be returning to the current release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play time: 48 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="freeware"></category><category term="2014"></category><category term="interactive fiction"></category><category term="platform independent"></category><category term="ifcomp 2014"></category><category term="Mike Gerwat"></category><category term="World War 1"></category></entry><entry><title>Software in the Age of Sneakernet: A Pictorial</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/commentary/software-in-the-age-of-sneakernet-a-pictorial.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:48:15-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-10-09:too-much-free-time/commentary/software-in-the-age-of-sneakernet-a-pictorial.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've spent the last few weeks fighting with a screen recorder to get a good demonstration of a hypertext word processor. A power outage caused me to lose my carefully prepared sample document, so while I recover from the pain of loss, let's take a look at something different: packaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, a lot of software is distributed digitally, and even software distributed on disk is often packaged in no more than a keep case, but it used to be that when you bought a piece of software, you really got your money's worth. Boxes, manuals, stacks of disks--you could measure software by the pound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/pict0057.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-919" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/pict0057.jpg?w=300" alt="DCIM100MEDIA" width="300" height="225" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Item number one: an upgrade kit for OS/2 2.0. I've scanned the &lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/os2front.jpg"&gt;front&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/os2back.jpg"&gt;back&lt;/a&gt;, if you'd like a better look. It's a fairly unassuming little box, but inside...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/pict0059.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-922" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/pict0059.jpg?w=300" alt="DCIM100MEDIA" width="300" height="225" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; different manuals ("Migrating to the OS/2 Workplace Shell", "Getting Started", "Using the Operating System", and "Installation Guide"), a pile of legal documentation, a rather shiny proof of license, &lt;em&gt;twenty-one&lt;/em&gt; 3.5" diskettes, and, to top it off, a roll of stickers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpwin.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-923" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpwin.jpg?w=261" alt="wpwin" width="261" height="300" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My copy of WordPerfect 5.2 for Windows came with a &lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpcatalog.jpg"&gt;catalog&lt;/a&gt; (Issue 4--collect them all, I suppose) full of ancillary material, including fonts and instructional videos, a heavy cardboard folder containing a &lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wplicense.jpg"&gt;license certificate&lt;/a&gt;, and, most importantly, one of these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpoverlay.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter wp-image-926 size-large" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpoverlay.jpg?w=1024" alt="wpoverlay" width="1024" height="121" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plastic keyboard overlay! Once, keyboards had room above the function keys for one of these, and for complex software, they were very necessary, at least until you got used to the software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpmini.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-927" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpmini.jpg?w=264" alt="wpmini" width="264" height="300" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you didn't always need a hefty manual--particularly if you already owned one. This 'additional license' version of WordPerfect 5.1 (suggested retail price: $295 US) contains a license certificate, a keyboard overlay, and not much else. From the back of the box:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Additional License Package is sold to you based on your certification that you are an authorized and licensed user of this version of this WordPerfect Corporation ("WPCorp") software product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This package includes a license and templates, but does not include manuals of disks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full-size software box for basically just a piece of paper. Dead tree edition, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Nihongo Word Processor v1.10</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/application/nihongo-word-processor-v110.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-09-20:too-much-free-time/application/nihongo-word-processor-v110.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The second X68k word processor I'll look at is the "SHARP X68000 日本語ワードプロセッサ Ver 1.10", produced circa 1990 by Sharp itself. It is credited with programming by H. Nakamoto and management by H. Tanaka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Nihongo Word Processor v1.10" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/nihongo-word-processor-v1-10.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For being only about two years newer, Sharp's Nihongo Word Processor (henceforth, NWP) looks &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; nicer than &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/application/ew.html"&gt;EW&lt;/a&gt;. Its interface reminds me very much of classic Macintosh programs. Coincidentally, the Mac also used a Motorola 68000 CPU, though somehow I doubt it influenced interface design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides being pretty, NWP is a perfectly serviceable word processor, with the standard features, plus one very neat divergence from the norm: on the right side of the screen is a pinboard with two notes attached to it. These represent the dual clipboard arrangement NWP uses. The left clipboard holds text which has been cut, and the right text which has been copied. There are separate paste commands for each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a minor thing, perhaps, but it's exactly the kind of uniqueness that makes me interested in software from this era. At this time, the clipboard functionality was provided by each program individually, rather than by the operating system (and its associated standard libraries), so the implementation is a conscious choice by the developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you look further back in software history, you can see different interface paradigms contending against one another for mindshare, each representing a different developer's idea about how the interface ought to be. Single clipboard with no history won this particular battle, though there are outliers like emacs's kill ring or the various 'clipboard managers' that provide something extra for the power user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://homepage1.nifty.com/dreamwave/x680x0/database/soft/word.htm"&gt;It looks like&lt;/a&gt; NWP shipped with certain models of the X68k. A positive bargain!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1990"></category><category term="X68000"></category><category term="word processor"></category><category term="interface"></category></entry><entry><title>EW</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/application/ew.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T19:24:25-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-09-19:too-much-free-time/application/ew.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now that I've looked at the two major players on PC, let's take a look at some word processors for other platforms, beginning with the Sharp X68000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EW" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/ew.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This word processor is identified as "X68000 Word Processor &amp;lt;&amp;lt; EW &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Version 1.20O", a 1988 release by EAST Co., Ltd. (which company &lt;a href="http://www.est.co.jp/"&gt;still exists&lt;/a&gt;, by the way).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EW looks quite similar to other word processors from the eighties: simply and ugly, including the (inexplicable!) choice to display hard returns on screen. Its ruler also measures not the size of the text on the page, but the number of columns occupied by the text. Fully 96 (half-width) columns are available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You interact with the program's extended features by either pressing escape to select from the menu, or pressing control key combinations to access other functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EW doesn't have quite the feature set of WordPerfect, but it's much lighter--roughly 900k, of which 388k is the dictionary. Being small may not be sufficient excuse for being ugly and limited, though: if my brief foray into &lt;a href="http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~uv2s-oob/x68/index.html"&gt;historic Japanese sources&lt;/a&gt; (vintage 1989/1990--practically ancient!) doesn't mislead me, EW wasn't a well-regarded piece of software.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1988"></category><category term="word processor"></category><category term="X68000"></category></entry><entry><title>Microsoft Word 5.0 (DOS) &amp; Microsoft Word 1.1 (Windows)</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/application/microsoft-word-50-dos-microsoft-word-11-windows.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T19:29:22-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-09-19:too-much-free-time/application/microsoft-word-50-dos-microsoft-word-11-windows.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like the last post, this one is a double feature. Sadly, unlike WordPerfect 5.1, which was released for both DOS and Windows with the same version number, MS Word used different numbers for is DOS and Windows version. So I've arbitrarily picked a DOS and Windows version each released at around the same time as WordPerfect 5.1 to look at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MS Word 5.0 for DOS" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/word_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On first glance, MS Word 5.0 for DOS, released in 1989, looks fairly similar to WordPerfect 5.1. It's a big blue screen with some status info at the bottom. But that's not quite all. In Word, the toolbar is constantly visible at the bottom, taking up several lines, and the text entry area is surrounded by a box. This box isn't just for show, though: you can choose to split the view into many different windows, which each may contain different documents. In practice, splitting the screen into more than two windows is probably not very useful, since the available space will be tiny, but it's still a nice feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the toolbar at the bottom, though, that's a waste of space. They should have just devoted a bit of space on the bottom line to say "Menu: Esc", or something, instead. I give them half credit for the interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MS Word 1.1 for Windows" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/krnl386_004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MS Word 1.1 for Windows, released in 1990, looks more like what we're familiar with from Word. With the standard menu-and-toolbar interface, it's a fairly usable word processor, even if it has some quirks in the display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Word 1.1 does have a big flaw, though: when I tried to open in Word 1.1 the document I made in Word for DOS, it actually crashed DOSBox! It did successfully open the document I made in WordPerfect 5.1, though... I think I'm going to have to give this point to WordPerfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Libreoffice" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/2014-09-18_22-17-59.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, opening the documents I made in either the DOS or Windows version of Word in Libreoffice yields a bunch of garbage. I know that &lt;em&gt;technically&lt;/em&gt; it's not Word's fault if a piece of software written a quarter century later doesn't properly import its documents, but it's still a sad lack of longevity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, 1989's version of MS Word had some neat tricks with the multi-window interface, but I prefer the minimalist (and less-space-wasting) WordPerfect interface. WordPerfect 5.1 for Windows looks better than Word 1.1 for Windows, too, though both were apparently rather buggy, so they'll be winning no awards: above all, software must &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WordPerfect was still king of word processors at this point, but over the course of the 90s, its crown would be stolen by Word, leaving the once-mighty application little more than an also-ran, relegated to filling out the OEM software stack of budget PCs.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1989"></category><category term="1990"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="Windows"></category><category term="word processor"></category></entry><entry><title>WordPerfect 5.1</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/application/wordperfect-51.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T19:36:06-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-09-16:too-much-free-time/application/wordperfect-51.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Technically, this blog is meant to be about video games. But I've written about &lt;a href="http://tmft.wordpress.com/2014/03/04/toshiba-t-3100-2/" title="Toshiba T-3100"&gt;hardware&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://tmft.wordpress.com/2013/06/05/ahoy-1-january-1984/" title="Ahoy! #1 (January 1984)"&gt;magazines&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://tmft.wordpress.com/2014/03/21/a-parents-guide-to-computer-games/" title="A Parent’s Guide to Computer Games"&gt;books&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-text-editor.html" title="First Impressions: Text Editor"&gt;whatever this is&lt;/a&gt;, so I figure anything fitting broadly under the retrocomputing banner is fair game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="WordPerfect 5.1+ title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/wp_000.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one may be familiar to you. WordPerfect 5.1, released in 1989, was quite a popular word processor, and it persisted for many years. In fact, &lt;a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~em36/wpdos/"&gt;it seems that&lt;/a&gt; people still want to use it to this day. It was used in my keyboarding class, in high school, so this is a bit of nostalgia for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A blank blue screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/wp_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you first open WordPerfect 5.1, you're greeted with a blank, blue screen, plus some details about the current position of the cursor. I'm fairly sure this violates a few interface design principles. On the other hand, considering that WordPerfect &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/2014-09-15_20-58-13.jpg"&gt;cost hundreds of dollars&lt;/a&gt;, perhaps they expected people to be willing to read the manual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Formatting demonstration" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/wp_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you know how to use it, WordPerfect 5.1 is a powerful word processor, capable of doing pretty much anything you'd like. More modern word processors may be prettier, but all of the basic functions were there. The image above is what WordPerfect calls draft mode--a semi-WYSIWYG display suitable for general use. You could also turn on 'reveal codes' mode, which displays markup in a manner reminiscent of HTML or BBCode:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blank, blue screen is just so... [Italc On]inviting[Italc Off]... wouldn't you say?[HRt]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, when printed, the document would actually use italic or bold text, or whatever other formatting was selected. WordPerfect was intended, after all, for preparing documents for print, not for display on a computer screen. All of the various options could be accessed either though a menu (activated with Alt+=) or through some combination of modifier and function keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="WordPerfect 5.1 for Windows" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/krnl386_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Windows version of WordPerfect 5.1, released in 1991, defaults to a WYSIWYG view that should seem familiar modern computer users. It does still support draft mode and 'reveal codes' mode, for those who long for the (shall we say) simplicity of the DOS version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never used the Windows version of WordPerfect 5.1, back in the nineties. The word on the internet seems to be that it's very buggy, which is a shame, since it seems like a fairly usable word processor, otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="LibreOffice displaying the WordPerfect file" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/2014-09-15_19-49-43.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just for fun, I tried just double-clicking the document I saved in WP 5.1 for DOS, opening it in LibreOffice. As you can see, it opens and renders flawlessly, despite the programs being released 25 years apart--a true standard-bearer for backwards compatibility! It makes me wonder if the &lt;a href="http://www.wordperfect.com/us/"&gt;present incarnation of WordPerfect&lt;/a&gt; could do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could spend pages discussing all the features of WordPerfect 5.1, but I really just wanted a quick look at it, to allow for comparison, so this much will suffice. I'll write similar overviews of other contemporary word processors (Coming soon! Maybe.) and other applications, to show some of the variety in software on the market. There was a great deal of evolution in a fairly short time, so it should be interesting to see how they compare.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1989"></category><category term="1991"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="Windows 3.x"></category><category term="word processor"></category></entry><entry><title>A Parent's Guide to Computer Games</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/book/a-parents-guide-to-computer-games.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-27T15:29:12-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-03-21:too-much-free-time/book/a-parents-guide-to-computer-games.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my quest to save marginal game-related information from the depths of obscurity, I came across this book, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0967512743/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=0967512743&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=tmft-20"&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Parent's Guide to Computer Games&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Craig Wessel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0967512743/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=0967512743&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=tmft-20"&gt;&lt;img alt="cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Book/images/parentsguide-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its back cover is very ominous:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your kids know what "RPG" means. &lt;big&gt;Do you?&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, it's a fairly decent book, given its focus. The first half is given to discussing generalities: the game platforms of the day (Windows, Macintosh, N64, Game Boy, PS1, PS2, Dreamcast); game platforms to come (Xbox, Gamecube, Game Boy Advance, even Linux is given a few paragraphs); surprisingly, a brief mention of emulation, specifically Bleem and Bleemcast; discussion of the various types and genres of games; a few pages devoted to online games, including specifically EverQuest and Ultima Online; finally, an explanation of the ESRB's rating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second half, of course, is devoted to the games, including one to three page reviews of each featured game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Reviews TOC 1" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Book/images/parentsguide-reviewtoc1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Reviews TOC 2" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Book/images/parentsguide-reviewtoc2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've uploaded the table of contents for the review section, above. It includes many notable games, including &lt;em&gt;Age of Empires 2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Deux Ex&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Diablo 2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Half-Life&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Civilization 2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Roller Coaster Tycoon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sim City 3000&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Sims&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;StarCraft&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Unreal Tournament&lt;/em&gt; in its "Hot Titles" section, and a fair mix of others (from &lt;em&gt;Icewind Dale&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Who Wants To Be A Millionaire?&lt;/em&gt;) in the other sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book was published in 2000, so it's only about 14 years old, today. That said, I think it's worth looking back to see just how things were perceived even as recently as that. The book predicts that Sony wouldn't be able to do much about Bleem, and notes, of Linux, that "game developers have embraced the operating system", though it's cautious about Linux's future prospects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm looking at some other examples of this type of book, as well. Secondary materials won't be forgotten, if I have anything to say about it!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="2000"></category><category term="Craig Wessel"></category></entry><entry><title>IFComp 2010: Under, In Erebus</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2010-under-in-erebus.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T19:00:38-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2010-10-21:too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2010-under-in-erebus.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Under, In Erebus&lt;/em&gt; by Brian Rapp is an interactive fiction game entered in the 2010 interactive fiction competition. You've accidentally boarded the wrong train, and when it stops, you're in a dark and unusual place. How will you get home?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This post contains spoilers. Read at your own risk.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt; is severely under-hinted. I solved very few of the puzzles without using the hints. Actually, I didn't even figure out that the booths were used for spelling out objects until I read the hints. It wasn't even entirely clear that you &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; trying to escape. For all I knew, you were supposed to make friends with the cyclops and learn his secret of eternal life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the puzzles felt positively obtuse. Spelling out PUB in order to get a drink? Was there some hint that I missed? Making a cup and a tub were pretty obvious, but that's pretty much all I managed alone. And the ending puzzle is absolutely impossible to guess, as far as I can tell. "You could use some assistance in escaping from Erebus. A student who will follow your instructions would be ideal." Why would I even consider that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some other problems, too. It was necessary to repeatedly travel around collecting ingredients (or, rather, letters) to try out puzzle solutions. Every time I needed a pea I had to go get one, open the pod, then use it. Eventually I just collected a big stack of bees and peas and dropped them near the booths, but I still had to make trips for the tea, ewes, and eye. I get that, from an in-game perspective, there should only be one eye at a time (though it reappearing sort of ruins that), but there could have been a whole flock of sheep I could herd to the booths, and I could have poured a small amount of tea out of the tub, leaving it little diminished. It was also a pain to have to take things out of the pack repeatedly. I'm of the opinion that if there's no good reason to restrict the player's inventory size, you shouldn't do it--I believe players will forgive at least that failure of realism in service to playability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt; wasn't all bad, though: there were some nice responses; the various 'bonus' words you could make were amusing--though not amusing enough to make me want to make them all, given the painfully large amount of work involved in making just one word; the changes in the response to examining yourself were nice; the fact that the backpack became a wristpack was a nice bit of attention to detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess there were some things I didn't explore. I couldn't work out how to explore the pit, though the ten points I got for making it would seem to indicate there's more to it. Maybe I should have tried "TILT"? But it's too late now, and I don't think I'll ever go back to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I regret that &lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt;'s shortcomings so outweighed its successes. The environment seemed like it might be fun, and I do enjoy wordplay--&lt;em&gt;Ad Verbum&lt;/em&gt; is one of my favorite games. But everything I did in &lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt; just felt like slow work. With better hinting and an easier way to create the words, &lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt; could be a pretty solid game. As it stands, though, it's just more trouble than it's worth.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="2010"></category><category term="interactive fiction"></category><category term="platform independent"></category><category term="Brian Rapp"></category><category term="fantasy"></category><category term="ifcomp 2010"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="wordplay"></category></entry><entry><title>Sonic 4 is Disappointing</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/uncategorized/sonic-4-is-disappointing.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T01:19:24-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2010-10-12:too-much-free-time/uncategorized/sonic-4-is-disappointing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been looking forward to Sonic 4 for several months now. The fact that a new, but retro-styled Sonic game would be coming to the Wii seemed like a dream come true. It was only a few months ago that I dusted off Sonic 3 &amp;amp; Knuckles for a play-through; it's always a fun way to spend a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, Sonic 4 doesn't live up to its predecessor--not by a long shot. It just does so many things wrong: the physics is bad, the game looks perpetually zoomed in, and the levels are unoriginal and rely on the homing attack thing way too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physics: Sonic stops moving when you stop pressing forward. It doesn't matter if you were running full speed and made a leap to get over a pit--when you let go of the forward button, Sonic drops like a hedgehog-shaped rock. Why? In the old games, a good part of the fun was getting up to full speed and bouncing over or past enemies so you never have to slow down. And on the topic of speed: it feels like Sonic takes far too long to speed up, and moving slowly is boring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 'zoomed in' look: Sonic is &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; in the middle of the screen, and you can only see a few steps on either side of you. When you're running at full speed (always remembering not to let go of the forward button), you have &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; time to react to enemies suddenly popping up in front of you. There go your rings, and, more importantly, your speed. Time to crawl back up to speed again. It seems like the game is designed to have you slowly walking up to enemies, killing them with the homing attack, and then moving on to the next segment, at least, when you aren't being moved about by the dozens of boosters liberally scattered around. And speaking of such things...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The levels and the homing attack: the levels in many ways feel like inferior copies of classic &lt;em&gt;Sonic&lt;/em&gt; levels. I guess that they were just making an homage to those games, which is fine, but there are way too many similarities. I'd have been happy with just the wrecking-ball type of boss fight from &lt;em&gt;Sonic 1&lt;/em&gt;, for that. There are lots of repetitive segments, too, which is odd for a &lt;em&gt;Sonic&lt;/em&gt; game--I've always felt that the diversity of the levels was one of the great things about the earlier games. In &lt;em&gt;Sonic 4&lt;/em&gt;, it sometimes felt like the only time the level changed up was when they were about to fling you blindly into a bunch of enemies you're supposed to mash on the homing attack button to defeat. Yeah, I get it. Sonic can attack them from mid-air and cross gaps and things. Lovely. But how many times am I going to be pulling off the same trick? I've got a lot of more specific criticisms of the levels, but I think those should probably wait until I've played a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, &lt;em&gt;Sonic 4&lt;/em&gt; is just disappointing. I was hoping for--and, naively, expecting--a great game, but what I got was just an okay platform game with none of the charm of the older games. I really don't think it's worth the $15, which is a shame.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The Wizard's Castle</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/the-wizards-castle.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T18:51:22-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2010-02-23:too-much-free-time/game/the-wizards-castle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Wizard's Castle&lt;/em&gt;, published for DOS in 1981 by International PC Owners is an early dungeon crawl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Intro" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/castle_000.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoiding the word 'year'? Check. Awesome apostrophes? Check. Journey from which no adventurer has ever returned? Yep! Let's make a journey to the cave of cliches! Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cliched-and-basically-nonexistent plot aside, &lt;em&gt;The Wizard's Castle&lt;/em&gt; is actually a pretty solid game. You start by choosing some basic stats for your character (race, sex, strength/intelligence/dexterity, equipment), and off you go to explore the castle and hunt for the incredible *ORB OF ZOT*. You're aided in your endeavour by a map of the dungeon which is meant to fill in as you explore or use items that reveal information about the dungeon, like flares or the lamp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Map" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/castle_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in the version I played, the map is already filled in, which I guess is a bug; I'm told later ports give you a properly blank map to start with. One annoying thing about this game is that the map legend is on the help screen, so you have to keep switching between the map and legend until you learn the meaning of the map symbols. Similarly, the player's stats are only shown upon moving into a room, so you have to move around to check them. There is plenty of room on the right for both of these, I think. Another, more minor problem is that you must press 'M' whenever you wish to show the map; since that is likely to be all the time, it means that the game consists of lots of &lt;code&gt;EMSMEEM&lt;/code&gt;, manually checking the map every few moves. It would have benefited greatly from just automatically showing the map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map issues aside, how is the game? Well, let's have a look at the map: the player is on the square marked by angle brackets above; to the west is a monster; to the east is a sinkhole, which drops the player down a level; to the south is a flare, which would ordinarily be very useful, as it lights up the area around the player, but is, in this version, useless due to the map being all filled in. Monsters can be fought, fled from, or bribed, though some (trolls, ogres, dragons) don't seem to be damaged by the sword I had, so it may be impossible to (successfully) fight some of them. Sinkholes cause the player to fall down a level, and stairs can lead either up or down. Items, such as flares, gold, and treasure, will be picked up automatically, and can be used or (in the case of gold and treasure) traded with the vendors the player will encounter in the dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successfully navigating the dungeon involves carefully planning your route, lest you find yourself very dead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dead again" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/castle_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all fights should be avoided, though. With the lamp, it's possible to tell precisely what monster is in an adjacent square, and the weaker ones can be fought for large sums of gold, which is very handy. However, it's not only the fights that can be hazardous: magic pools can be drunk from, and may either help or harm the player, and books, too,  can be either very helpful or very dangerous--even the chests might explode or release toxic gas upon being opened. After picking up some treasures, the player can choose to leave the dungeon, or continue on, seeking the ultimate treasure in the form of the Orb of Zot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking the Orb of Zot is harder than it sounds. Scattered about are orbs the player can gaze into in order to gain information about what lies in the dungeon--these will occasionally tell the player that the Orb of Zot is in some particular location, but this isn't as helpful as it seems--the orbs may claim that the Orb is in several different locations, and I have yet to find it by going to these locations. I suspect there is a trick to it, but I've not spent enough time to puzzle it out. For now, I'm satisfied with picking up the lesser treasures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DYWYPI?" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/castle_004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dungeon is randomized each time you play, so if you care to, you can play as many times as you like without running out of new dungeons to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom line: &lt;em&gt;The Wizard's Castle&lt;/em&gt; is pretty fun. I'm sure it would have been much more challenging to collect the treasures if the map had functioned correctly in the version I played, so I suspect this game would be good for a few hours distraction here and there. There's something satisfying about a nice dungeon crawl, and for all its simplicity and lack of polish, &lt;em&gt;The Wizard's Castle&lt;/em&gt; isn't bad at all. It's no Nethack, but it's worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1981"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="dungeon crawl"></category><category term="RPG"></category><category term="fantasy"></category><category term="International PC Owners"></category><category term="Joseph R. Power"></category></entry><entry><title>Phage Wars 2</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/phage-wars-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T19:08:25-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2009-08-22:too-much-free-time/game/phage-wars-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.kongregate.com/games/ArmorGames/phage-wars-2/?referrer=Sopoforic"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phage Wars 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Armor Games is a fun little flash game, though not a terribly difficult one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Main screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/phagewars2-snap113.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Phage Wars 2, the player is a lab tech whose goal is to create the most powerful virus ever. This is accomplished by playing through the 32 stages (called 'experiments') and adding the gene proteins you discover to your virus in order to improve its strength, speed, defense, agility, and ability to reproduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Beginning an experiment" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/phagewars2-snap115.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the 32 experiments contains a number of cells and enemy viruses. The player can choose to infect cells or attack cells which are already infected by an enemy virus in order to take them over. Once a cell is infected, the virus inside begins to reproduce, so the player can then attack other cells. The stage is won when no enemy viruses remain. A new gene protein is discovered after beating each stage for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/phagewars2-snap118.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between experiments, the player has the opportunity to add the gene proteins to his virus. The proteins have varying effects, and can increase some statistics while decreasing others. Additionally, each protein takes up a certain amount of space in the virus's genetic code, so the player must choose between them to create the strongest virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Upgrading a virus" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/phagewars2-snap119.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The controls are pretty simple: click and drag from a source cell to a destination cell to send your viruses to infect or attack. To send viruses from multiple cells to a single destination, just drag over all the desired source cells. The best strategy I found was to infect as many cells as possible as quickly as possible, and then to attack the enemy viruses once all the empty cells had been claimed. To support this, I improved the attack, defense, and reproductive ability of my virus, though I understand that improving speed and agility is also a valid strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here lies the problem with the game: it's really much too easy. With a decent bonus to reproduction, the viruses will fill a cell quite quickly, and with a decent bonus to attack, it's not hard to destroy any enemy virus given a mostly-full source cell. The game requires a little juggling to make sure you maintain control of your cells, but it's not really hard to do, and by improving defense even that becomes very easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phage Wars 2&lt;/em&gt; has basically identical gameplay to its predecessor, with the exception of the ability to add proteins to improve your virus rather than simply choosing a virus at the beginning. The idea isn't totally original to this series, either--the concept is basically just &lt;em&gt;Risk&lt;/em&gt;, and the game's particulars are rather reminiscent, to me, of the primordial soup subgame in &lt;em&gt;The Time Warp of Dr. Brain&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of difficulty and originality aren't really so bad that they ruin the game; it still pretty fun. To be honest, I'm not sure I know any way to make the game more difficult without also making it frustrating or otherwise less fun. As for the originality--well, some ideas are reused because they work, and I'd say this is one of them. Give the game a shot if you've got the time to spare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gameplay: 7/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The controls are nice, the mechanics are understandable, the concept is solid. It's a little too easy, though, and the main skill required, I think, is clicking and dragging &lt;em&gt;very quickly&lt;/em&gt; at the beginning.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Story: 2/5&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The story's just an excuse for the gameplay, so this only counts half. On the other hand, the story's obviously just an excuse, so minus some points.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Graphics: 9/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The graphics are polished and lovely. Minus a point since the foreground and background were sometimes hard to distinguish, and there was nothing that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; impressed me.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Audio: 5/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;There's nothing really wrong with the audio, but it didn't stand out in any way. Some more interesting audio might have made my interest in the game last a bit longer.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Personal Slant: 6/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I enjoyed the game, though I think the sequencing part was a little dull, and the lack of difficulty made it drag on a little by the end.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Total: 6.4/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phage Wars 2&lt;/em&gt; is worth a play, though not a replay. In fact, I'd say that the moment you begin to become bored with it, you should abandon it--it's just more of the same, and the ending isn't worth plodding through the game if you're not enjoying it. It only takes a few minutes to play through the first few levels, though, and those few minutes are worth it.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;</summary><category term="freeware"></category><category term="2009"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="flash"></category><category term="strategy"></category><category term="Armor Games Inc."></category><category term="interesting interface"></category></entry><entry><title>Tetris</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/tetris.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-30T22:02:45-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-10-28:too-much-free-time/game/tetris.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt;, the classic falling blocks game, was released by Nintendo in November 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly, &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt; needs no introduction. There are hundreds of implementations of this simple, yet challenging game. Nintendo's 1989 offering for the NES is quite well-done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Menu" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are few options. The player can choose between A-type and B-type games, and select which music should be played, if any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Play begins" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The A-type game is simply pieces falling endlessly, with the goal being to obtain the highest score. The six types of pieces fall starting at the top of the screen, and proceed toward the bottom. While they are in the air, the player can move them left and right, rotate them, or cause them to drop more quickly. Some of the pieces are rarer than others, so it's necessary to choose where the pieces are placed with care--you can't count on a line appearing whenever you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Play continues" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_005.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every ten lines you complete, the game's speed increases one level and the colors of the blocks change. The more lines you eliminate at once, the more points you get, with a Tetris (four lines removed) scoring the most points. You also score more points if you're at a higher level--each line is worth ten times as much at level nine as it is at level zero, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="About to lose" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_008.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the game progresses and the blocks fall faster, the game becomes much more difficult. If the blocks reach too high on the screen, the music will speed up as a warning. If the blocks reach the top of the screen, you lose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="B-type game" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The B-type game is similar to the A-type game, except that rather than playing endlessly, the goal is to remove 25 lines at a particular level, and with a set height of blocks added at the start. Now the lines count down, and the game ends upon removing all 25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="B-type complete" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_007.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're given a score based on the level and height you selected, as well as the points accumulated while removing the lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="High score" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_009.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your score is high enough, you can enter your name on the high score table, and be known far and wide as a Tetris master--at least until you power off the console. I played this game a lot when I was younger, though I suppose I wasn't that skilled at it--on a good game, I'd get about 110 lines, though I understand that experts can get over 200.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though this is a fairly old game, it's quite nice. The graphics are nice, clear, and colorful (though the color schemes for some of the levels are a bit ugly), the music is good, and the gameplay is simply excellent. The B-type game offers a nice, quick challenge if you're in the mood, and the A-type is nice for slightly longer gaming sessions. Of course, there are many other versions of Tetris, which may be better or worse than this one (I hear that Tengen's NES version is superior), but Nintendo's &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt; is definitely worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gameplay&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;10/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Graphics&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;8/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sound/Music&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;8/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Personal Slant&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;10/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Overall&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;9/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;</summary><category term="NES"></category><category term="1989"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="falling blocks"></category><category term="Nintendo"></category></entry><entry><title>Pinball</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/pinball.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-27T06:40:04-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-10-27:too-much-free-time/game/pinball.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pinball&lt;/em&gt; was released by Nintendo in February 1984 in Japan and October 1985 in the US, and, as the name suggests, is a simple pinball game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pinball title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Pinball_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pinball&lt;/em&gt; features two pinball screens and a bonus screen. An extra ball is awarded for every 50,000 points, and the flipper becomes invisible while your score is between 100,000 and 150,000 points. Each screen has a way to place a block post between the flippers to prevent your ball from falling, and several special ways to get large amounts of points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pinball upper screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Pinball_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After releasing the plunger, the ball goes to the top screen, and falls through one of the three lanes to score 500 or 1,000 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting the ball through the green lane on the right causes the penguins in the center to act like a slot machine, and hitting the moving pink slot target will cause them to stop on either 3, 7, or a penguin. Matching them scores points and causes a block post to appear between the flippers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting the ball through the upper left lane causes the seals to bounce balls on their noses, activating the 100 point bumper in the middle. Between this and the dots filling that lane, this scores 2,800 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The counter at the upper left awards the shown number of points when it is hit, increasing each time by 100 points, up to a maximum of 1,000 points. It resets when you put the ball through the left lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four targets on the left award a 1,000 point bonus when you hit them all. The hole on the lower right only kicks the ball back if you fall in it; the ball exits from that hole when leaving the bonus screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Falling from the top screen doesn't lose the ball, but rather drops it to the bottom screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pinball lower screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Pinball_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bottom screen, there are a few features of note. Passing through the lanes at the top flips over the cards. When all the cards are flipped, a 5,000 point bonus is awarded, and a block post appears between the flippers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitting all seven of the targets on the left awards a 1,000 point bonus, and removes the pink bars on the right, allowing you to relaunch the ball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three eggs above the flippers hatch when hit once, disappear when hit again, and turn back to eggs when you pass over them a third time. Causing all three eggs to be hatched at the same time adds stoppers to the outlanes. Between this and the cards, it is possible to keep the ball quite safe, though these stoppers do disappear once they are hit once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the hole in the upper right leads to the bonus stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pinball bonus screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Pinball_006.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the bonus stage, you control Mario. You're supposed to run beneath the ball to bounce it back up, rather like breakout. Unlike breakout, though, the floor beneath the girl shrinks when the column of lights beneath it are turned the same color. The colors change whenever the ball rolls over them. When the floor disappears, the girl falls, and you must catch her and allow her to walk off to the left or right. Doing so awards you 10,000 points and restarts the bonus level. The level ends if the ball falls to the sides, which causes it to pop out of the hole on the top screen, or the girl falls without you catching her, which will cost you your ball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the whole game! The difference between the A and B games is that the ball is heavier in the B games, making them more challenging. It's a fairly simple game, but it's pretty well done. The controls are pretty good and the graphics aren't bad. There's no music in the game, but the sound effects are nice. I'd say that if you like pinball games, this one is worth a try. It lacks the accurate physics and detail of later pinball games, but it's still a fun diversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gameplay: 8/10
Graphics: 7/10
Sound/Music: 6/10
Personal Slant: 8/10
Overall: 7.25/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(An &lt;a href="http://joz3d.net/documents/Pinball.txt"&gt;FAQ by Luke Jozwiak&lt;/a&gt; provided the details on the point values.)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="good"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="pinball"></category><category term="Nintendo"></category><category term="1984"></category></entry><entry><title>SkyRoads</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/skyroads.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-25T03:46:31-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-07-16:too-much-free-time/game/skyroads.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SkyRoads&lt;/em&gt; was a driving game released in 1993 by Bluemoon Interactive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkyRoads title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/skyroads_000.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The object is to complete each road, passing through the pipe at the end. There are various obstacles along the way, including blocks or gaps that must be jumped over, pipes that must be entered or avoided, as well as the threat of running out of oxygen or fuel before the end of the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkyRoads gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/skyroads_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early roads are quite easy, requiring little jumping. Each can be completed on the first play through with minimal difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkyRoads gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/skyroads_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the game progresses, though, the roads become more difficult, some requiring multiple tries to complete. This could be a good or a bad thing, depending on your perspective. Sometimes, pipes hide walls or missing sections of floor, which will kill you, so you must remember to avoid those pipes the next time through. In my opinion, since the levels are so short (each requiring less than one minute), this required repetition does not detract from the gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkyRoads gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/skyroads_004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SkyRoads&lt;/em&gt; has nice graphics, and very nice music as well, together with fun gameplay--the makings of a great game. It does fall short on replay value, though. While the roads are still nice after you've beaten them, there's no real incentive to play them again--no way to try to beat your best times (which wouldn't really matter, since most roads will be completed at maximum speed anyway), no secrets to be found, and only one way through the road, with minor variations. Despite this fault, though, &lt;em&gt;SkyRoads&lt;/em&gt; is well worth playing, even if you might not play it much after you've completed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below you'll find a video of the first three roads, Red Heat, being completed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gheKz3pK7u0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SkyRoads&lt;/em&gt; can be &lt;a href="http://www.bluemoon.ee/history/skyroads/"&gt;downloaded for free from Bluemoon Interactive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="freeware"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="1993"></category><category term="driving"></category><category term="Bluemoon Interactive"></category><category term="futuristic"></category><category term="liberated games"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Novatron</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-novatron.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-30T21:37:58-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-06-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-novatron.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Novatron&lt;/em&gt; is a DOS lightcycles (tron) game released by VeriSoft Works in 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/novatron_000.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been quite a lot of lightcycle games through the years--&lt;a href="http://www.mobygames.com/game-group/light-cycle-games"&gt;MobyGames lists 10&lt;/a&gt;, though I suspect it's missing quite a few. The most recent that MobyGames lists is for the Xbox 360 (&lt;a href="http://www.mobygames.com/game/tron"&gt;Tron&lt;/a&gt;, 2008), and the oldest is for the Intellivision (&lt;a href="http://www.mobygames.com/game/snafu"&gt;Snafu&lt;/a&gt;, 1981). &lt;em&gt;Novatron&lt;/em&gt; is a fairly old example of this type of game, and it shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/novatron_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the graphics are fairly nice, and the controls responsive, &lt;em&gt;Novatron&lt;/em&gt; is quite difficult to play. The keys used to control your lightcycle are F9, F10, Insert, and Delete, which are poorly placed. It's been a while since I've seen an original IBM PC keyboard, but I don't recall that they would have been in ideal positions on that keyboard either. Positioning aside, I kept confusing which of Ins and Del turned which direction, so I lost quite badly. Too, I found it difficult to tell just how much space I had left before running into a wall, probably due to the viewing angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the game isn't terrible, but isn't really worth playing when there are so many better examples of the type. Personally, I'd recommend &lt;a href="http://www.mobygames.com/game/armagetron-advanced"&gt;Armagetron Advanced&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1982"></category><category term="arcade"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="lightcycle"></category><category term="VeriSoft Works"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: The Adventures of Rad Gravity</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-the-adventures-of-rad-gravity.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-30T21:30:37-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-05-22:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-the-adventures-of-rad-gravity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Adventures of Rad Gravity&lt;/em&gt; is a platform shooter by Activision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-rad-gravity_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game begins by giving us our mission: to discover teleport locations by infiltrating the computers on the planet below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Intro" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-rad-gravity_006.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this goal in mind, we are sent down to begin. The enemies are rather odd, and the level designs leave a great deal to be desired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-rad-gravity_009.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn't obvious from these pictures, but certain of the blocks which make up the scene can be walked through, and others must be jumped over. There's no particular indication which is which, although I think that they are color coded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Robots" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-rad-gravity_012.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After passing through a few screens, we encounter these robots, which are initially very difficult to kill. The weapon we have at the beginning is some sort of energy knife or something, and its range is about the width of Rad's body. The robots move fairly quickly, so you have to tap the button pretty quickly as well in order to kill them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you move through the level you pick up powerups, including additional life bars and a gun, which seems to be slightly less powerful than the knife, but has the enormous advantage of being a ranged weapon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screen with teleporter" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-rad-gravity_015.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all the levels are identical, as you can see in the above screencap. The thing with the up/down arrows on it is a sort of elevator (which I got stuck on and had to jump to disembark), and the thing center-right is a teleporter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Terrible design" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-rad-gravity_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we see an example of extremely stupid level design. Every horizontal line is a surface, so you can--if you release buttons at the right moments--move yourself to whichever height you desire. Of course, it's much easier to dodge the electricity (which is bouncing between the ceiling and floor) when you're at the bottom of the screen, since it gives you more time to run past it, so there's no particular reason you want to be anywhere except on the the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it weren't for the rather painful graphics and horrible level design, &lt;em&gt;Rad Gravity&lt;/em&gt; might be a pretty good game. If you can stomach those faults, give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="NES"></category><category term="platformer"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="Activision"></category><category term="Interplay"></category><category term="futuristic"></category><category term="1990"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Zombie Nation</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-zombie-nation.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-26T23:32:07-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-03-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-zombie-nation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This time a shoot-em-up, &lt;em&gt;Zombie Nation&lt;/em&gt;, known in Japan as &lt;em&gt;Abarenbou Tengu&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Zombie Nation title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Zombie-Nation_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abarenbou Tengu title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Abarenbou-Tengu_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot of &lt;em&gt;Zombie Nation&lt;/em&gt; is odd, and I doubt that it matters. You're a flying samurai head, and you are apparently charged with rescuing America, the population of which has been turned into zombies. Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Zombie Nation gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Zombie-Nation_006.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were lasers scattered liberally throughout the level which reduced me to one life unit, so I died quite often at first. You have only one life, and limited continues, each of which returns you to the beginning of the level. Therefore I relied on save states to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that you are meant to rescue people who will occasionally fly out of buildings and things as you destroy them. Collecting four such people allows you to have more shots on the screen at a time, and eventually allows you to use a special attack which targets the whole screen. The first level culminates in a battle against the Statue of Liberty, which seems to have become a medusa at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Zombie Nation Statue of Liberty" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Zombie-Nation_020.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abarenbou Tengu&lt;/em&gt; is rather different. In a stunning display of needless changes in localisation, the samurai head you play as in &lt;em&gt;Zombie Nation&lt;/em&gt; is not present in the Japanese version. Instead, you play as a tengu head. The Statue of Liberty, too, was changed in localisation: in the Japanese version, it was not a medusa, and was red besides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abarenbou Tengu Statue of Liberty" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Abarenbou-Tengu_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I played further on &lt;em&gt;Abarenbou Tengu&lt;/em&gt; than &lt;em&gt;Zombie Nation&lt;/em&gt;, so I do not know how things changed after the first boss, but I do have to wonder how they might have changed the second boss:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abarenbou Tengu second boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Abarenbou-Tengu_008.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it's better not to know. Still, despite the odd localisation and initial difficulty, &lt;em&gt;Zombie Nation&lt;/em&gt; is a pretty good game. Certainly worth wasting a few minutes on.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="good"></category><category term="horizontal scrolling shooter"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="1990"></category><category term="KAZe Co. Ltd."></category><category term="Live Planning"></category><category term="Meldac"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: The Adventures of Captain Comic</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-the-adventures-of-captain-comic.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-30T19:14:24-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-03-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-the-adventures-of-captain-comic.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This time a platformer, &lt;em&gt;The Adventures of Captain Comic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-captain-comic_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/the-adventures-of-bayou-billy.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Adventures of Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Captain Comic&lt;/em&gt; is frustratingly difficult. Most of the time, there are three or four enemies on the screen at once, and they respawn a few seconds after you kill them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-captain-comic_007.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The level designs place many obstacles in your path, and though the controls are generally quite responsive, I found it difficult to manage the fine control to move on small platforms without running off into the abyss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay 2" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-captain-comic_010.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were several different areas with unique backgrounds and enemies, each of which had different movement patters. This variety is nice, but unfortunately each area is similarly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mountainous background" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-captain-comic_011.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Stone walls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-captain-comic_013.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Weird" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/adventures-of-captain-comic_015.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having read a guide after my attempt, it seems like some of the areas seemed so totally unfair because I tackled the game in the wrong order, but the complete lack of guidance made it impossible to know just what I ought to have done. Were it not for the benefit of save states, I'm sure I would have given up before seeing the third area, for the effort to get through the game is completely disproportionate to the entertainment granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game looks fairly good for an old NES game, the music, though very repetitive, isn't bad, and the controls are good if a bit too enthusiastic. Unfortunately, the game's difficulty more than compensates for these positive points. I can't recommend the game unless you don't mind frustration.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="NES"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="platformer"></category><category term="Color Dreams"></category><category term="futuristic"></category><category term="1989"></category></entry><entry><title>The Adventures of Bayou Billy</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/the-adventures-of-bayou-billy.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-30T19:00:39-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-03-16:too-much-free-time/game/the-adventures-of-bayou-billy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Adventures of Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; is a beat-em-up, with a driving and shooting game thrown in for variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; won't be winning any awards for its plot. Some bad guy has kidnapped your girlfriend, and you have to rescue her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Intro" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He's even kind enough to let you know that you will be encountering obstacles on your way to his estate. What a nice guy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game behaves pretty much like your bog standard beat-em-up, with a button for punch and one for kick, and pressing both together doing a flying kick. You can pick up weapons that you knock out of your enemies' hands and to use against them. The difference, though, is that &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. It's not so bad against one enemy, but you'll find yourself fighting against three at a time, who are not stunned when you hit them, take many hits to kill, and are fairly quick-moving as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fighting three enemies" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_15.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, they are also fairly stupid, and will happily walk around in circles without hitting you, if you move just a bit. They also occasionally drop food, which heals you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans aren't your only foes, though. You'll also encounter crocodiles in the water, which are quick moving and can attack you when you're near the water's edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Crocodiles" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_17.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got to the right side of this screen, it didn't scroll any further, and since I couldn't seem to harm the crocodile, I quickly died.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Game over" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_18.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game does include, as I mentioned, a driving subgame and a shooting subgame, which can be accessed from the practice menu, and apparently appear as levels later in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Driving game" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_23.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shooting game" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_21.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither of these subgames was anything spectacular, although the shooting game did have the benefit of being playable with or without a zapper. Nice, since the emulated zapper uses the mouse, and playing with my laptop's touchpad was very difficult indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Adventures of Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; was called &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt; in Japan, and was considerably easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mad City title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/mad-city_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My feeling from playing a few minutes is that the enemies died in about a third as many hits in &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt;. Furthermore, the screen that wouldn't go anywhere in &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; and had only crocodiles had divers in &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt;, and continued once I defeated them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mad City gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/mad-city_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No crocodiles in &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt;. Perhaps I didn't step on a trigger or something while playing &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt;, which caused the divers not to appear. Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I think that &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt; is probably better than &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt;, although I only played either one for a few minutes. My final opinion is that &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt; is worth playing, but I'd avoid &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt;, since its difficulty is just not fun.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="NES"></category><category term="beat 'em up"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="Konami"></category><category term="1988"></category><category term="1989"></category></entry><entry><title>Donkey</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/donkey.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T14:23:11-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-01-01:too-much-free-time/game/donkey.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After far too long a break, a new game. Or, rather, quite an old one: Donkey, written in 1981 by Bill Gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DONKEY.BAS title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/donkeyqb_000.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donkey was written&lt;sup id="fnref:wp"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:wp" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as a way to showcase the capabilities of the BASIC programming language which shipped with new IBM PCs. Therefore one might expect it to be a very simple game--and simple it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/donkeyqb_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The object is to avoid the donkeys in the road as you drive. The controls consist of only a single button, the space bar, which is used to switch lanes. Each time you successfully pass a donkey, your car moves a bit closer to the top of the screen, so that it will be more difficult to switch in time to miss the next one. If you hit a donkey, the donkeys are given a point, you explode, and you start over:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Game Over" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/donkeyqb_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every eleventh donkey that you pass, you are reset to the center of the screen and given a point. The game keeps track of the score, but there's no particular reward for reaching any certain score; the game just continues until you exit. As simple and unrewarding as this game is, that's likely to be fairly soon after starting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: I've added a video demonstrating the gameplay below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7QL3yyYJ3Y&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the game &lt;a href="http://drivey.com/DONKEYQB.BAS.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:wp"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Wikipedia, which has &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DONKEY.BAS"&gt;a lengthy article&lt;/a&gt;, if you'd like to read more.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:wp" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="1981"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="driving"></category><category term="Bill Gates"></category></entry><entry><title>Abadox: The Deadly Inner War</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/abadox-the-deadly-inner-war.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-27T00:17:11-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-12-08:too-much-free-time/game/abadox-the-deadly-inner-war.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A shooter this time, and a pretty good one, at that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this game incorporates powerups, you begin, as in most similar games, with nothing but a pathetic little pea-shooter and no armor, moving very slowly indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox beginning" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_04.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had quite a bit of difficulty dodging the shots from the--very bizarre--enemies at first, but then I got a speed powerup and a couple of options and the dodging was no longer necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After progressing through a level that looked like it was made of worms, or possibly intestines, and fighting enemies like flying mouths and eyeballs, I reached the first boss: some sort of skeletal dog with bits of flesh still clinging to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox first boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_09.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This boss just jumps around a bit while releasing a few shots, so it was no problem to kill. After defeating this boss, we proceed to the second level, which is rather like the first except in much closer quarters and with various obstacles which required dodging. At the end of this level was the second boss, a face made of intestines, with its eyes floating about in front of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox second boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_13.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This boss, too, was no trouble to beat, although it did destroy my options. However, after destroying this boss, the game changed from a horizontal scroller to a vertical scroller--which scrolled from bottom to top, just to make it more confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox third level" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_16.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I died a bit into this level, since I had no options and some enemies are only half-destroyed by a shot. This game is much better than most of the others I've tried. I liked Super R-Type for the SNES better, but this is also a pretty good example of the genre. Worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="good"></category><category term="horizontal scrolling shooter"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="Dynamic Planning Inc."></category><category term="ITL Co. Ltd."></category><category term="Natsume Co. Ltd."></category><category term="1989"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 8 Eyes</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-8-eyes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-27T00:51:28-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-12-08:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-8-eyes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This game is like &lt;em&gt;Castlevania&lt;/em&gt;, except much, much harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="8 Eyes title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/8-Eyes_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the game begins, you select which country to play in first. I understand that it's something like &lt;em&gt;Megaman&lt;/em&gt;: play in the wrong order, and the game is much harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="8 Eyes stage select" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/8-Eyes_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game really looks quite a lot like &lt;em&gt;Castlevania&lt;/em&gt;, and plays similarly, too, with one major difference: in &lt;em&gt;8 Eyes&lt;/em&gt;, you have a falcon with you, and some enemies can only be destroyed by the falcon. Unfortunately, you only have control over the falcon when there are two players--the second player controls the falcon. With one player, the falcon just flies left and right, and your control is limited to telling it to swoop down to attack or return to your shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="8 Eyes gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/8-Eyes_07.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result of this lack of control is that the game is way too hard with one player, and I can't imagine why anyone would play it just to control the falcon. Give this one a miss.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bad"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="platformer"></category><category term="Thinking Rabbit"></category><category term="Taxan USA Corp."></category><category term="1988"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 75 Bingo</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-75-bingo.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-25T08:12:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-28:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-75-bingo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A horrible slots game by Sachen, the company that gave us &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-tasac.html"&gt;Tasac&lt;/a&gt; and other gems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="75 Bingo title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/75-Bingo_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have much to say on this one, since I don't see the point of these games that are totally luck-based gambling simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="75 Bingo gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/75-Bingo_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Like other Sachen games, and other gambling sims, just don't bother.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1990"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="slots"></category><category term="gambling"></category><category term="Sachen"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Brickout!</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-brickout.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-25T03:28:12-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-26:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-brickout.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A foray into other consoles with the Intellivision's 'Brickout!'. It's clear just from the name that it's a Breakout clone, but is it a good one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Brickout! title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Brickout!_1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short answer: No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's very simple. You get 20 lives, you move the bat along the bottom of the screen, the ball destroys the bricks it hits. This wouldn't make it a bad game, by itself; it would only make it an overly simple one. The problem is that this game has such bad collision detection that the ball will slide through the corners of the bricks occasionally. It will get stuck in a row and take the whole row out. Not bad things, right? They make it easier, yes? They do, but I'd prefer some challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Brickout! gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Brickout!_2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the game does provide that. Since the game is old (I suppose), its controls are somewhat lacking, and the framerate is just bad. The ball is minuscule in comparison to the bricks or the bat, so it's not that hard to lose track of it. It's not too clear, when the ball is moving at a shallow angle, where the ball will be when it is on a level with the bat. Now, perhaps these things are minor, and I am just bad at the game, but either way, I won't soon play this again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Arkanoid is better in every way. Play it instead.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1981"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="breakout"></category><category term="Intellivision"></category><category term="Mattel"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Parallel World</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-parallel-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-26T23:54:51-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-26:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-parallel-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A puzzle game, of the push-things-around-to-reach-the-exit variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parallel World title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Parallel-World_07.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find our heroes on the school roof (I guess) when a hole opens in the sky and sucks them in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parallel World opening" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Parallel-World_13.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the sky is made of glass in Japan. They find themselves before a castle, and, being clueless schoolchildren, they enter. In order to leave this world they have to pass through the rooms of the castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parallel World gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Parallel-World_16.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each room has several creatures and several blocks which can be pushed around the room. Push a block over a creature to kill it and get a key, which opens the exit to the room. You can jump atop the white blocks and then walk to the exit. You may only walk along the blue paths on the blocks you slide around; fortunately these blocks can be rotated. If you push the blocks against the wall in the wrong order, you're screwed. You can restart the level, but you get very few lives so you'd best get it right the first time. There appear to be four rooms to each world, and a number of worlds unknown to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parallel World gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/Impressions/images/Parallel-World_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: It's not too bad as puzzles go. It's been done before, but for puzzle fans this one is worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="decent"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="puzzle"></category><category term="EIM Ltd."></category><category term="Varie Corporation"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Palamedes</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-palamedes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-22T00:14:56-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-25:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-palamedes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A rather fun &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt;-like game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Palamedes title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Palamedes_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Palamedes isn't quite the usual falling blocks game. Instead, rows of blocks approach and it is your task to remove them by hitting them with matching block. You select which block to throw at them (from a cycle of six) and try to keep up. It's something like Bust-a-Move, I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Palamedes gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Palamedes_11.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few false starts, I made it to stage six. This one would probably be easier using a gamepad, but mine's loaned out, so take the apparent difficulty with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: It's a good game. These are few and far between, so I'd check this one out if you're a fan of falling blocks games.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="falling blocks"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="Hot-B Co. Ltd."></category><category term="Natsume Co. Ltd."></category><category term="1990"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Bump'n'Jump</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-bumpnjump.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-21T23:57:54-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-25:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-bumpnjump.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's a driving game, of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bump'n'Jump title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japanese version was called Buggy Popper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bump'n'Jump title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/buggy-popper_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start with a car driving away, with someone crying "Help me!" inside. Being the heroic gamers that we are, this is sufficient motivation for us to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Help me!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of the game seems to be that we have a car which can jump at will, and we like to land on other cars and destroy them for no reason. Well, except that it gets us points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Jumping car" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_09.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever designed these roads needs to be shot. Apparently in the bizarro-world that this game take place in, cars normally have the ability to jump (but only yours does, as far as I saw), so in order to save some of the cost of roads, they just left out some sections. Yeah, that's logical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Road, interrupted" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_13.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, we can forgive some strangeness if it's a good game, right? Of course we can. Unfortunately, the designers decided to take all of my good will and stomp on it, by putting in a ludicrously long repair sequence when you drive over one of the bonuses on the road:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Repair sequence" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_15.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You sit at this screen for upwards of fifteen seconds while text flashes on screen assuring you that they are repairing your car and have not, in fact, run off with your money and girlfriend to Tijuana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you finally finish the first level, you are treated to the second level, in which the brilliant road designer decided that if there wasn't any water to break up the monotony, then we'd just have to build some raised roads to block the lower ones instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Not a tunnel!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_21.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are helpful black areas that &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; like tunnels to pass through. They aren't. They are just there because the designer was sadistic. The problem is that if you jump any time when the little jump warning box is on the screen, you'll end up hitting the wall anyway, and it's much harder to figure out when to jump when you have to make it over a wall instead of just some water. You can't really tell how tall the thing is, since, as we all know, you should never do 3D on an NES.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we crash and die, and the game ends. I don't know what happened to that car we were chasing earlier. Probably some girl was kidnapped, and since we couldn't catch her she was raped and killed. And it's all the road designer's fault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: There are worse games. This is like a mix of Spy Hunter and Roger Rabbit, and it doesn't do well at emulating either. Play Spy Hunter instead, since it had the good sense to give you guns for killing people with, and was a better game anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="driving"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="1986"></category><category term="1988"></category><category term="Data East"></category><category term="Vic Tokai Inc."></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 3D Block</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-3d-block.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T14:11:42-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-25:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-3d-block.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A falling blocks game, which appears from the title screen to be an adult game. Is it? See inside:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="3D Block title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3d-block_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll answer now, to spare you any anxiety: if it's an adult game, no one will ever know, because it's impossible to get anything done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Starting off" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3d-block_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not too hard to rotate the shape when it's at the top, but once it gets further down it's nigh impossible to tell how it's oriented. Furthermore, it's very hard to tell at a glance what the levels below the top are like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3d-block_06.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what is that box on the lower right? Is it supposed to help me guide my blocks? It shows four blocks per level. There are sixteen blocks per level in truth. I don't know how this is meant to help, but it's about as useful as dictionary with every other letter missing--you know there's more to it, but it doesn't do you any good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all these faults, the only thing that let me complete the first level was the the blocks fall slowly--painfully slowly. You can press start to drop the block all the way, but there's no way to move it down just a bit. When the second level comes, though, this isn't a problem. Where the first level was far too slow, the second level is impossibly fast. The blocks fall completely in about a second, which is nowhere near enough time to orient them, much less position them accurately. So, we get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="About to lose" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3d-block_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the game is thankfully over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: This game shows why 3D should not be done on an NES. The 2D Tetris games are pretty good on the NES, so if you want falling blocks, play those instead.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bad"></category><category term="falling blocks"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="old 3d games"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Tenchi wo Kurau II - Shokatsu Koumei Den</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-tenchi-wo-kurau-ii-shokatsu-koumei-den.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T14:03:08-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-tenchi-wo-kurau-ii-shokatsu-koumei-den.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An RPG, and one that actually seems pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tenchi wo Kurau II title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a very lengthy opening, we find ourselves in the castle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Castle" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon leaving the building, we gain two party members, and begin to explore the town. One issue I found was that although everyone starts with equipment, it's not equipped, so you have to equip five items to each character, one at a time. An equip all feature would have been nice, but I guess you only have to do it once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Town" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_06.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Overworld" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_07.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graphics are actually pretty good for an NES game, as you see when walking around the town and then entering the world map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't play all the way through this, but it looks good so I probably will. One thing of note is that you don't have hit points in this game. Instead, you are (nominally) commanding an army, so you lose troops when attacked, and your damage is dependent on how many troops you have left. Strangely enough, though, herbs still 'heal' you and a revive still restores you to full 'health.' Possibly the designers weren't thinking it through very carefully. The battle screen is reminiscent of Final Fantasy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Battle" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you win battles, you gain experience, and your army levels up. You gain some kind of skills, but I haven't played enough to see what they do yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: This seems like a good game. The graphics are nice and the battle system, while simple, is reasonably good. If it continues as it has begun, this game will probably be worth playing through.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="good"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="rpg"></category><category term="ancient China"></category><category term="Capcom"></category><category term="fan translation"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Tasac</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-tasac.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T12:17:36-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-tasac.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tasac is a vertical scrolling shooter by Sachen, and it sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tasac title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Tasac_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title screen looks pretty cool, so one might expect the game to have decent graphics, or something. Most of your in-game time is spent in a position like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tasac gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Tasac_04.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no real challenge in this part, except that the laser-like weapon you start with sucks, and the upgrades suck even more. When you get to the end, the boss appears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tasac pre-boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Tasac_07.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can't kill it yet. In fact, you can fly right over it. Why is the boss there before you're able to interact with it? I don't know. But the game carries on just as if the boss weren't there. In fact, it carries on the same way even once you can fight the boss--the random enemies keep appearing, there's just a boss on the screen at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tasac boss fight" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Tasac_09.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the boss shoots a pretty large number of projectiles at you, they're not hard to dodge. If the weapon weren't so stupidly slow and hard to use, they boss wouldn't be even slightly difficult. As it is, the boss just takes a little longer than it ought to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second level was just like the first. I think that the boss was slightly rounder, but I don't really care to recall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Pointless. It's just a below average vertical scroller.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bad"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="futuristic"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="Sachen"></category><category term="Thin Chen"></category><category term="1992"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Text Editor</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-text-editor.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T11:58:27-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-text-editor.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Original title: ""РЕДАКТОР ТЕКСТОВ"". In Latin characters: "REDAKTOR TEKSTOV".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broken, probably. I'm not sure what it's supposed to do, but it just shows several screens of text then loops. Nestopia complains about bad header info, or something. The first and last screens are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Text Editor first screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Text-Editor_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Text Editor last screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Text-Editor_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: According to the &lt;a href="http://bootleggames.wikia.com/wiki/A._Chudov#.D0.A0.D0.B5.D0.B4.D0.B0.D0.BA.D1.82.D0.BE.D1.80_.D1.82.D0.B5.D0.BA.D1.81.D1.82.D0.B0_.28Text_Editor.29"&gt;BootlegGames Wiki&lt;/a&gt;, this program needs a printer. I wasn't aware that such a thing existed, but apparently some Famiclones had a printer port. The more you know!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="unplayable"></category><category term="nes"></category><category term="1996"></category><category term="A. Chudov"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Flying Warriors</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-flying-warriors.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T11:32:35-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-flying-warriors.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yeah, it's out of order. I hit 'random game I haven't played' and I got this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Flying Warriors title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flying Warriors. It sounds like some kind of shooter maybe. Airplane game. That's cool, I liked 1943. So, what do I get? Castlevania if it sucked and had a boring training sequence. But before training, some important wisdom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Advice" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, on to the training. Since the designers went to all the trouble of putting in training, this game must have some complex controls, or something. Let's see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_20.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_05.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_22.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_06.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, that's right. Toward automatically blocks at the right level, and B automatically punches at the right level. You get to practice these complex manoeuvres several times before you grasp them fully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Success!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_09.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes! I am a master! I can now go out and make the world a better place! But, first, a practice match against sensei. Well, sure. I'm a master now. Piece of cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fight with sensei" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_10.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we fight and... he beats me down. Badly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Have you no pride!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_11.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it's back to training. Never mind that training couldn't possibly help me, and that a monkey could manage these controls. So, we train again, he declares me a master again, we fight again, I lose again. Repeat. Repeat...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I win. So we get a scene change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rick is alone in the mountains as usual." src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_12.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Empty screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_13.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the game begins with an exciting... empty screen! I have to move off it to an entirely different scene to get to the actual game. What was the point? Why waste my time putting this scene in if there's nothing here? The next scene is some kind of mountain area, which kind of matches with the description, but that does not explain what the point of this last scene was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_15.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after that painfully long training and practice fight, we expect challenge, yes? But the enemies all die in one hit! The hardest part is managing the movement controls, since it seems to be impossible to make Rick (our hero) jump the way you want him to. After a couple of screens full of these zombie-like wimps, we enter a cave, filled with more of the same, as well as the far more dangerous bottomless pits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pits?" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_17.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, these pits are so much more dangerous, that they even kill the enemies, who just jump off like lemmings. But, remember how I said that jumping correctly was the hardest part?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pits!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_18.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I too jump off like a lemming. The game tells me that Rick doesn't let this stop him. Fortunately, it does stop me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: You can't skip the long intro, you have to go through boring training and practice fights, only to get to a game that acts like a bad rip off of Castlevania. Better to leave this one alone.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1990"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="beat 'em up"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="Culture Brain Inc."></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: The 3-D Battles of World Runner</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-the-3-d-battles-of-world-runner.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T11:23:05-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-the-3-d-battles-of-world-runner.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Run around, avoiding the enemies, until you get to the boss. Then button mash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="World Runner title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3-D-Battles-of-World-Runner_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's kind of dull, since all there is to do is move forward, at varying rates of speed, and jump. You get a rocket, which actually looks like a pink fireball when you use it, but I can't imagine what it's good for since any enemy you hit with the rocket wouldn't have been there when you actually run past it, and the enemies which weren't in your line of fire will run into you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="World Runner gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3-D-Battles-of-World-Runner_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to jump over some pits as you go. Since the game doesn't have real 3D, you can't really tell how wide the pits are until you're in the air, so you have to try to land in the right spot by changing speed in the air. Sometimes you have only a small area to land, so I kept overshooting or actually smacking my face on the edge of the ground and then sliding down to my death. When you finish the level you fight this centipede-thing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="World Runner boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3-D-Battles-of-World-Runner_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a picture from before the game starts, since I neglected to take a screenshot while actually fighting it. Suffice to say you fire the pink rocket-fireballs at it until it dies. I have no clue how it is intended to hurt you, since it doesn't seem to have any rockets of its own. Or arms. Or anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second level is like the first, except grey. I assume that the others follow suit. The game also has an anaglyph 3D mode, activated by pressing select. I have not yet mustered the courage to try this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: It's not bad, but it wouldn't hold my attention for long.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1987"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="anaglyph 3d"></category><category term="Acclaim"></category><category term="Disk Original Group"></category><category term="Square Co. Ltd."></category><category term="old 3d games"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 1991 Du Ma Racing</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1991-du-ma-racing.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T11:12:10-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1991-du-ma-racing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's horse racing. The title screen greets us, for some reason, with some weird balloon horse things bouncing around:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1991 Du Ma Racing title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1991-Du-Ma-Racing_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the balloon horses were supposed to liven the game up. If so, they failed. There are two modes: race mode and gamble mode. I didn't want to contemplate what might cause you to want to bet on a race controlled by the computer with no real rewards, so I chose race mode. Presumably, it was intended for two players, but it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1991 Du Ma Racing gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1991-Du-Ma-Racing_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the little bars with the red balls near them, at the bottom? Those balls were bouncing up and down, and the object was (I deduced) to hit B when yours crossed the center line. Sort of like DDR. Even granted you could find someone else bored enough to play this game, it would be pointless, since it's all but impossible &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to hit the button at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only is this the only apparent 'challenge' in the game, it goes on forever. You have to go all the way around the track hitting B every half second or so, and that's it. The view switches to overhead when you're on the side of the track, but that doesn't matter since it's still exactly the same worthless game it was when the view was side-on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Don't bother.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1991"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="gambling"></category><category term="horse racing"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="Idea-Tek Inc."></category><category term="Super Mega"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 1944</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1944.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T22:00:27-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1944.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's a pirate version of &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1943-the-battle-of-midway.html"&gt;1943&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1944 title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1944_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only change that I noted between this and 1943 is that holding down the fire button, rather than charging the weapon, yields a very fast auto-fire. Otherwise, identical:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1944 gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1944_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Play 1943 instead.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="NES"></category><category term="pirate game"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="World War 2"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 1943 - The Battle of Midway</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1943-the-battle-of-midway.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T21:28:02-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1943-the-battle-of-midway.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An excellent conversion of Capcom's vertical scrolling shooter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1943 title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one has more features than &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1942.html"&gt;its predecessor&lt;/a&gt;, such as the ability to configure your plane before you start:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1943 customization" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, when you start, it tells you briefly what your target is. In the first level, it's Rikaku, the Japanese Heavy Cruiser:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1943 target" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is 1942, you're piloting a P-38, which you can improve as you play by picking up better weapons and energy bonuses. The gameplay is the same, too: fire at the enemy planes (and ships) while avoiding being hit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1943 ingame" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_04.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the level, you fight Rikaku, which is heavily armed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rikaku" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you win, you move on to the next level. There are a total of 24 levels in the NES version, as compared to 16 in the arcade version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: 1943 has excellent sound, good graphics, smooth controls, and addictive gameplay. Definitely worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1988"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="Capcom"></category><category term="World War 2"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 10-Yard Fight</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-10-yard-fight.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T20:06:29-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-10-yard-fight.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's an American football game. I don't know the rules of the game, but, honestly, I doubt that matters for this game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="10-Yard Fight title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/10-Yard-Fight_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start the game running down the field, and quickly meet the opposing team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="10-Yard Fight gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/10-Yard-Fight_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scene repeats, with the referee running out every few seconds, since I'm tackled every time I move. I don't think there are any controls except 'throw ball before running' and 'run.' Once I mastered this fiendishly clever control scheme, it was just a matter of seeing whether my patience or the field ran out first. It turns out that my patience won, so I got the joy of getting to the end--then starting again! Pathetic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little searching tells me that if I had been willing to spend a half hour playing this game, I'd have gotten to play defense as well as offense. Fortunately, everyone seems to agree that it's be stupid to waste that much time on this one, so I'll bow to the wisdom of the internets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Don't play this one.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Irem Corp."></category><category term="1985"></category><category term="American football"></category><category term="NES"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 1942</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1942.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T21:22:44-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1942.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The famous vertical scrolling shooter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1942 title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1942_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not too bad. You control the plane, which moves pretty smoothly, and shoot the enemies. A rather basic idea, but workable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1942 title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1942_04.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this one just doesn't measure up to its sequel, 1943. I can't show it in a screenshot, but the sound was annoying--there was a beeping sort of sound going on while playing. The graphics, too, aren't as good as in 1943.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Play &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/impressions/first-impressions-1943-the-battle-of-midway.html"&gt;1943&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1986"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="Capcom"></category><category term="World War 2"></category></entry></feed>