<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Too Much Free Time</title><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/feeds/application.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/</id><updated>2015-06-19T19:24:25-04:00</updated><entry><title>Nihongo Word Processor v1.10</title><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/nihongo-word-processor-v110.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-09-20:too-much-free-time/nihongo-word-processor-v110.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The second X68k word processor I'll look at is the "SHARP X68000 日本語ワードプロセッサ Ver 1.10", produced circa 1990 by Sharp itself. It is credited with programming by H. Nakamoto and management by H. Tanaka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Nihongo Word Processor v1.10" src="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/nihongo-word-processor-v1-10.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For being only about two years newer, Sharp's Nihongo Word Processor (henceforth, NWP) looks &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; nicer than &lt;a href="http://tmft.wordpress.com/2014/09/19/ew/"&gt;EW&lt;/a&gt;. Its interface reminds me very much of classic Macintosh programs. Coincidentally, the Mac also used a Motorola 68000 CPU, though somehow I doubt it influenced interface design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides being pretty, NWP is a perfectly serviceable word processor, with the standard features, plus one very neat divergence from the norm: on the right side of the screen is a pinboard with two notes attached to it. These represent the dual clipboard arrangement NWP uses. The left clipboard holds text which has been cut, and the right text which has been copied. There are separate paste commands for each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a minor thing, perhaps, but it's exactly the kind of uniqueness that makes me interested in software from this era. At this time, the clipboard functionality was provided by each program individually, rather than by the operating system (and its associated standard libraries), so the implementation is a conscious choice by the developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you look further back in software history, you can see different interface paradigms contending against one another for mindshare, each representing a different developer's idea about how the interface ought to be. Single clipboard with no history won this particular battle, though there are outliers like emacs's kill ring or the various 'clipboard managers' that provide something extra for the power user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://homepage1.nifty.com/dreamwave/x680x0/database/soft/word.htm"&gt;It looks like&lt;/a&gt; NWP shipped with certain models of the X68k. A positive bargain!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1990"></category><category term="X68000"></category><category term="word processor"></category><category term="interface"></category></entry><entry><title>EW</title><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/ew.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T19:24:25-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-09-19:too-much-free-time/ew.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now that I've looked at the two major players on PC, let's take a look at some word processors for other platforms, beginning with the Sharp X68000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="EW" src="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/ew.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This word processor is identified as "X68000 Word Processor &amp;lt;&amp;lt; EW &amp;gt;&amp;gt; Version 1.20O", a 1988 release by EAST Co., Ltd. (which company &lt;a href="http://www.est.co.jp/"&gt;still exists&lt;/a&gt;, by the way).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EW looks quite similar to other word processors from the eighties: simply and ugly, including the (inexplicable!) choice to display hard returns on screen. Its ruler also measures not the size of the text on the page, but the number of columns occupied by the text. Fully 96 (half-width) columns are available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You interact with the program's extended features by either pressing escape to select from the menu, or pressing control key combinations to access other functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EW doesn't have quite the feature set of WordPerfect, but it's much lighter--roughly 900k, of which 388k is the dictionary. Being small may not be sufficient excuse for being ugly and limited, though: if my brief foray into &lt;a href="http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~uv2s-oob/x68/index.html"&gt;historic Japanese sources&lt;/a&gt; (vintage 1989/1990--practically ancient!) doesn't mislead me, EW wasn't a well-regarded piece of software.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1988"></category><category term="word processor"></category><category term="X68000"></category></entry></feed>