<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Too Much Free Time</title><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/feeds/commentary.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/</id><updated>2015-06-21T00:08:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Classic Nintendo Games are (NP-)Hard by Aloupis et al.</title><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/classic-nintendo-games-are-np-hard-by-aloupis-et-al.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-21T00:08:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-06-20:too-much-free-time/classic-nintendo-games-are-np-hard-by-aloupis-et-al.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across an interesting paper on arXiv, "Classic Nintendo Games are (NP-)Hard" by Greg Aloupis, Erik D. Demaine, Alan Guo, and Giovanni Viglietta. The paper is originally from 2012, but it's been updated in February of this year with additional results. It's been mentioned a few times on the web, but I didn't see anyone give a satisfactory explanation of what the paper is really about. I'm not an expert, but I'll give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, though, the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We prove NP-hardness results for five of Nintendo's largest video game franchises: Mario, Donkey Kong, Legend of Zelda, Metroid, and Pokemon. Our results apply to Super Mario Bros. 1, 3, Lost Levels, and Super Mario World; Donkey Kong Country 1-3; all Legend of Zelda games except Zelda II: The Adventure of Link; all Metroid games; and all Pokemon role-playing games. For Mario and Donkey Kong, we show NP-completeness. In addition, we observe that several games in the Zelda series are PSPACE-complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does it all mean?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll go into some detail shortly, but I'd like to describe in broad strokes what this is (and isn't).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors look at how hard it is to answer the question: given a particular level layout, a starting point, and a finish point, is it possible to get from the start to the finish?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't about the levels actually in the games--in fact, it isn't really about the level design &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. What it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; about is the rules of the games. &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;, for example, has several well-known rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mushrooms make small Mario big.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touching enemies (or some other hazards) makes big Mario small, or kills small Mario.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mario can break bricks only if he's big.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stars make Mario temporarily invulnerable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mario can jump to a height of 4 tiles, or 5 when running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more rules, but you see the point. Importantly, the authors specify that their results are about an &lt;em&gt;idealized&lt;/em&gt; version of the rules. In other words, glitches don't count. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the authors prove is that if you turn someone loose with a level editor, they can design a level for which it is very hard to determine whether it's even possible to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do this by showing that you can implement a problem called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_satisfiability_problem#3-satisfiability"&gt;3-satisfiability problem&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;3-SAT&lt;/em&gt;) in each of the games. Think of someone &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3FoNJeYY-Oc"&gt;using redstone to make &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Minecraft&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and you've got the general idea. 3-SAT is known to be NP-complete (read as: difficult), and the game it's implemented in must be &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; as hard as 3-SAT. Those problems are called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-hard"&gt;NP-hard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3-satisfiability problem is to determine if, given a boolean formula of a certain form, it is possible to set the variables (which can be either true or false) in such a way that the whole formula comes out true. A two-variable example of 3-SAT might be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;(y is TRUE | x is TRUE | x is TRUE)
    AND
(x is FALSE | y is TRUE | y is TRUE)
    AND
(x is FALSE | y is FALSE | y is FALSE)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Don't be alarmed by the duplication. The reason for writing that way will be apparent later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt; in 3-SAT means that each sub-expression (in parentheses) can have at most 3 parts. In this case, each has only two parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three sub-expressions must be true for the formula to be true, and a sub-expression is true if &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of its components (which are separated by pipes) is true. In logic-speak, it's a conjunction of several disjunctions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's pretty easy to see that this expression is true if y is true (satisfying the first part) and x is false (satisfying the other two). But, what if there were fifty or a hundred or a billion sub-expressions? That would be harder to tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Requirements for 3-SAT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be able to implement 3-SAT, you need a few components. You need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A starting point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A finishing point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to pick whether a variable is true or false&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way for those choices to either impede or allow progress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to let paths cross without being able to change from one path to another&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last one is so that you can build big, complex paths. Without it, you'd be able to backtrack and mess things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors implement these components in 'gadgets', which are basically self-contained rooms or screens that can be connected to each other. They're the building blocks of the satisfiability puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gadgets in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll take a brief look at how the authors build these gadgets for &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;, as an example. This is going to be pretty much the same as what the authors say in the paper, so if you're feeling industrious, you can look at the paper and see how they put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Start&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start gadget is just where Mario starts the level--there's nothing to it. In general, the authors want Mario to be big throughout the level, so they put a mushroom at the beginning that will be required at the finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finish&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is trivial. It's just the flagpole. To make sure Mario stayed big throughout the level, you have him enter the screen with the flagpole in a corridor with a brick he must break to reach the flagpole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Finish gadget" src="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/aloupis2012-mario1-finish-gadget.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Variable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To pick whether a variable is true or false, Mario is given a screen with two possible paths--a vertical drop to either the left or right. Say left means "x is true" and right means "x is false". It doesn't matter which. The drops are long enough that Mario can't get back up, so once a choice is made, Mario can't go back and also take the other path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Clause and Check&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the most interesting (and important) gadget in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt; Take a look at it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Clause and Check gadget" src="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/aloupis2012-mario1-clause-gadget.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After making a choice and dropping from the Variable gadget, Mario will be led to (a series of) Clause gadgets. He enters one of the small open areas from the bottom--each one of them will have a path from a Variable gadget that leads to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each block contains a star, which will be trapped in the 'fence' when Mario hits the block. Later, Mario will come through the top part (that's the Check part of the gadget) and collect the star so that he can run through the Firebars. If Mario gets to the Check gadget without having hit the star block (thus satisfying the disjunction), he can't proceed--the Firebars will kill him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember our example of 3-SAT from earlier?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;(y is TRUE | x is TRUE | x is TRUE)
    AND
(x is FALSE | y is TRUE | y is TRUE)
    AND
(x is FALSE | y is FALSE | y is FALSE)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Imagine that the gadget pictured corresponds to the top disjunction, &lt;code&gt;(y is TRUE | x is TRUE | x is TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;. Then Mario will reach the left star block if he picked "y is TRUE" by dropping down the left side of the corresponding Variable gadget, and the middle and right star blocks by picking "x is TRUE" by dropping down the left side of &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; particular Variable gadget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if Mario picked "x is false" and "y is false"? Then he'd never get to the blocks and release the star, so when he got to the Check gadget, the Firebars would kill him. That means that both variables being false isn't a solution to the expression, and (equivalently) taking the right path at both variable gadgets won't let Mario finish the level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crossover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just a utility to let paths cross without Mario backtracking and making two different choices for one Variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Crossover gadget" src="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/aloupis2012-mario1-crossover-gadget.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mario comes in from the lower path, he can break the bricks and keep going up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If he comes in from the upper path, he can run into the Goomba to become small, head to the right, pick up the mushroom from the block, break the brick, and continue to the right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small Mario can't break the bricks in the middle to go up, and big Mario can't get through the narrow paths to go to the right. Big Mario also can't break the bricks and then go back, because the drop on the left is too far for him to get back up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Putting it all together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can string together as many Variable, Clause, and Check gadgets as you need to make as big of a problem as you want. Since we know that 3-SAT is NP-complete, and we've just implemented 3-SAT in &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Bros.&lt;/em&gt;, we know that &lt;em&gt;SMB&lt;/em&gt; is NP-hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! If you've made it this far, then you've got the major idea of (part of) the paper. Pick up your CS degree on the way out the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other games, other problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't go into detail about the other sections of the paper, but if you've read this far, you should be able to read the paper and see what is being done. The proofs for other Mario games just make some modifications to the gadgets we looked at above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proofs for the Zelda games are different. They still work by implementing an NP-hard problem, but it's a different problem, and they implement it using the sliding blocks in the Zelda series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to know about the other games, or get more details, take look at the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Caveat lector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done my best, here, but I'm not an expert. I've got a BS in math, not a doctorate in computer science. If I've made some terrible mistake, it's all my fault (and I'd appreciate it if you'd let me know!), and I apologize for anything misleading, confusing, or dangerous that I've written. Always wear proper safety equipment when proving theorems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Aloupis2012v3]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Greg Aloupis &amp;amp; Erik D. Demaine &amp;amp; Alan Guo et al., &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1203.1895v3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Classic Nintendo Games are (NP-)Hard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,  (2012-03-08).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;</summary><category term="academic"></category><category term="computational complexity"></category><category term="Mario"></category><category term="Donkey Kong"></category><category term="Zelda"></category><category term="Metroid"></category><category term="Pokemon"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on Ferguson's Media Violence Paper</title><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/thoughts-on-fergusons-media-violence-paper.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-11-09:too-much-free-time/thoughts-on-fergusons-media-violence-paper.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My attention was directed to &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jcom.12129/full"&gt;a paper by Christopher J. Ferguson&lt;/a&gt;, to be published in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Communication&lt;/em&gt;, which argues that the common belief that there is a positive correlation between media violence and societal violence is false. The abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article presents 2 studies of the association of media violence rates with societal violence rates. In the first study, movie violence and homicide rates are examined across the 20th century and into the 21st (1920–2005). Throughout the mid-20th century small-to-moderate correlational relationships can be observed between movie violence and homicide rates in the United States. This trend reversed in the early and latter 20th century, with movie violence rates inversely related to homicide rates. In the second study, videogame violence consumption is examined against youth violence rates in the previous 2 decades. Videogame consumption is associated with a decline in youth violence rates. Results suggest that societal consumption of media violence is not predictive of increased societal violence rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The article, briefly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the full article is about twenty pages, I'll summarize it here, with a bit more detail than the abstract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ferguson begins by establishing that there is not general agreement in the literature as to correlation (much less causation) between media violence and societal violence. He particularly argues that that laboratory studies which show an increase in aggression (e.g. an increased tendency to fill in missing letters in words to create violent words) following consumption of violent media may not correspond to increased societal violence (e.g. homicide).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first study analyzes the relationship between violence in movies and homicide, between 1920 and 2005. To assess violence in movies, the top five grossing movies per year were taken at five-year intervals, and graded for violent content. This data was compared to statistics for murder and (non-negligent) homicide during the same years. Ferguson concludes that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together these data suggest that perceived correlations between movie and societal violence were associated with a chance concordance during the mid-20th century. Given that these phenomena were not in concordance in either the early or latter 20th century, it appears that efforts to establish causal connections between movie and societal violence based on a select set of decades were an ecological fallacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second study analyzes the relationship between violence in video games and youth violence for the years 1996 to 2011. Ferguson uses sales data from IMDb and the ESA and takes the ratings assigned by the ESRB as a proxy for violent content. He concludes that there is a "remarkably strong" inverse relationship between violent video game consumption and youth violence and that, although this is no indication of causality, "Evidence from societal data does not support claims of dramatic videogame violence effects on violence among youth."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Ferguson argues that alternate methods should be used in the future when assessing the effect of media consumption on behavior, and that professional organizations such as the APA should "retire their policy statements on media violence as such statements tend to be misleading and may cause more harm than good." Furthermore, "Arguably, given that the results from the effects paradigm have been weak and inconsistent, it may be time for scholars to make less rather than more conclusive statements to news media regarding media effects on society."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unaddressed questions and other problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ferguson's conclusion in the first study (namely that positive correlation between media violence and societal violence is limited to a mid-century concordance) seems undeniable. I am not similarly satisfied with the second study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious problem with the second study is that it addresses a period of only sixteen years, and in particular that it does not even consider whether the change in rate of youth violence differed before and after the introduction of video games. Given that Ferguson strongly criticized reliance on data from a limited time span in the first study, this is fairly damning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the second study does not argue that &lt;em&gt;generally&lt;/em&gt; increased video game consumption corresponds to an increase in the consumption of &lt;em&gt;violent&lt;/em&gt; video games &lt;em&gt;by youths&lt;/em&gt;. I freely admit that it is likely that this is true, but the study makes no mention of it. In general, I am not convinced by Ferguson's 'just look at the top five games according to IMDb' approach to analyzing the state of gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the study blithely dismisses any correlation between increased incarceration and decreased youth violence, on strength of &lt;a href="http://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ875143"&gt;a paper by Stahlkopf, Males, and Macallair&lt;/a&gt;. Based on its abstract, that paper only concludes that increased &lt;em&gt;juvenile&lt;/em&gt; incarceration does not lead to reduced crime (specifically in California). It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible that the full paper has more useful (for Ferguson) conclusions, but I do not have access to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourth, the graphs in the paper are unclear as to what exactly is depicted. Figure 3, "Societal videogame violence consumption and societal youth violence, 1996-2011.", is a double chart with yearly figures for the two measures in question, with scales ranging from 0-9000 for one and 0-40 for the other. 9000 what? 40 what? I have no idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifth, without commenting on the sensibility of the suggestions Ferguson makes, I would say that his statements in the "Theoretical implications" section are not supported by the studies. Ferguson argues that different theoretical approaches should be used in studying the relationship between media violence and societal violence, essentially by mentioning a variety of alternatives without arguing for their particular effectiveness. Such arguments would be better suited to a paper which actually considers the relative merit of the various approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sixth, the "Policy implications" section reads like a conspiracy theory. Selections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a matter of policy, consistent with the statement by the Consortium of Scholars (2013)...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...media-based policy statements released by professional organizations have so often been revealed to be flawed (e.g., Ferguson, 2013;Magid, 2011).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...it has been revealed that past policy statements were typically
developed by specially selected researchers heavily invested in antimedia views, with no dissenting voices (Ferguson, 2013).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, problems have been 'revealed' &lt;em&gt;by the author of this paper&lt;/em&gt;. The 'statement by the Consortium of Scholars' mentioned is an open letter of which Ferguson is a signatory, and the source of which is &lt;em&gt;Ferguson's personal website&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:homepage"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:homepage" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reference to Magid links to a paper published in &lt;em&gt;Pediatrics&lt;/em&gt; (by O'Keeffe and Clarke-Pearson), but the actual reference listed is to an article in &lt;em&gt;Huffington Post&lt;/em&gt; which responds to (and disputes) the journal article. Why Ferguson would obfuscatingly link to the article in &lt;em&gt;Pediatrics&lt;/em&gt; rather than the one in &lt;em&gt;HuffPo&lt;/em&gt; to which he actually referred is a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, take note of "...some scholars have argued...(Males, 2013)." That reference is not to a scholarly paper, but what seems to be simply an opinion piece published by YouthFacts.org.&lt;sup id="fnref:broken"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:broken" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the actual studies in the paper seem fairly inoffensive, but do not support the discussion. It seems very like Ferguson wanted to pontificate about perceived problems in his field, and conducted a couple of very minor studies in order to have an excuse for publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I have not studied psychology. I studied math at uni, so except insofar as the paper uses statistical analyses, I have no formal education relevant to this paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, as I do not have access to a university library, I have not been able to review all of the paper's references. It is possible that some or all of my objections were answered by the cited papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, I am (obviously) a gamer, and inclined to agree with the &lt;em&gt;results&lt;/em&gt; of the studies in this paper, despite my objections to the academic rigour of the paper. It is possible that I have been too lenient with the studies for this reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Ferguson2015]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Christopher J. Ferguson, &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jcom.12129/full"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does Media Violence Predict Societal Violence? It Depends on What You Look at and When&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Journal of Communication &lt;strong&gt;65&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; (2015), E1--E22.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Magid2011]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Larry Magid, &lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/larry-magid/facebook-depression-nonexistent_b_842733.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Facebook Depression': A Nonexistent Condition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, The Huffington Post (2011-03-30).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[OKeeffe2011]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Gwenn Schurgin O'Keeffe &amp;amp; Kathleen Clarke-Pearson &amp;amp; Council on Communications and Media, &lt;a href="http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/127/4/800.full"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The impact of social media on children, adolescents, and families&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Pediatrics &lt;strong&gt;127&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; (2011), 800--804.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Stahlkopf2010]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Christina Stahlkopf &amp;amp; Mike Males &amp;amp; Daniel Macallair, &lt;a href="http://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ875143"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Testing Incapacitation Theory Youth Crime and Incarceration in California&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Crime &amp;amp; Delinquency &lt;strong&gt;56&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; (2010), 253--268.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:homepage"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which, incidentally, &lt;a href="http://www.christopherjferguson.com/"&gt;looks more like the geocities homepage of a teenager&lt;/a&gt; than the website of a professional academic.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:homepage" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:broken"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a broken link, besides--&lt;a href="http://youthfacts.org/files/articles/bloomberg_guns2_06012013.html"&gt;here's a working one&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:broken" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="academic"></category><category term="Christopher J. Ferguson"></category><category term="violence"></category></entry><entry><title>Software in the Age of Sneakernet: A Pictorial</title><link href="http://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/software-in-the-age-of-sneakernet-a-pictorial.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:48:15-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-10-09:too-much-free-time/software-in-the-age-of-sneakernet-a-pictorial.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've spent the last few weeks fighting with a screen recorder to get a good demonstration of a hypertext word processor. A power outage caused me to lose my carefully prepared sample document, so while I recover from the pain of loss, let's take a look at something different: packaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, a lot of software is distributed digitally, and even software distributed on disk is often packaged in no more than a keep case, but it used to be that when you bought a piece of software, you really got your money's worth. Boxes, manuals, stacks of disks--you could measure software by the pound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/pict0057.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-919" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/pict0057.jpg?w=300" alt="DCIM100MEDIA" width="300" height="225" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Item number one: an upgrade kit for OS/2 2.0. I've scanned the &lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/os2front.jpg"&gt;front&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/os2back.jpg"&gt;back&lt;/a&gt;, if you'd like a better look. It's a fairly unassuming little box, but inside...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/pict0059.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-922" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/pict0059.jpg?w=300" alt="DCIM100MEDIA" width="300" height="225" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; different manuals ("Migrating to the OS/2 Workplace Shell", "Getting Started", "Using the Operating System", and "Installation Guide"), a pile of legal documentation, a rather shiny proof of license, &lt;em&gt;twenty-one&lt;/em&gt; 3.5" diskettes, and, to top it off, a roll of stickers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpwin.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-923" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpwin.jpg?w=261" alt="wpwin" width="261" height="300" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My copy of WordPerfect 5.2 for Windows came with a &lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpcatalog.jpg"&gt;catalog&lt;/a&gt; (Issue 4--collect them all, I suppose) full of ancillary material, including fonts and instructional videos, a heavy cardboard folder containing a &lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wplicense.jpg"&gt;license certificate&lt;/a&gt;, and, most importantly, one of these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpoverlay.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter wp-image-926 size-large" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpoverlay.jpg?w=1024" alt="wpoverlay" width="1024" height="121" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plastic keyboard overlay! Once, keyboards had room above the function keys for one of these, and for complex software, they were very necessary, at least until you got used to the software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpmini.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-927" src="https://tmft.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/wpmini.jpg?w=264" alt="wpmini" width="264" height="300" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you didn't always need a hefty manual--particularly if you already owned one. This 'additional license' version of WordPerfect 5.1 (suggested retail price: $295 US) contains a license certificate, a keyboard overlay, and not much else. From the back of the box:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Additional License Package is sold to you based on your certification that you are an authorized and licensed user of this version of this WordPerfect Corporation ("WPCorp") software product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This package includes a license and templates, but does not include manuals of disks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full-size software box for basically just a piece of paper. Dead tree edition, indeed.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>