<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Too Much Free Time</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/feeds/game.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/</id><updated>2015-07-01T19:26:48-04:00</updated><entry><title>TIS-100</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/tis-100.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T12:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-06-19:too-much-free-time/game/tis-100.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="TIS-100 opening screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/370360_2015-06-17_00004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I saw a new game from &lt;a href="http://www.zachtronics.com/"&gt;Zachtronics Industries&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;, which was released &lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/370360/"&gt;on Steam&lt;/a&gt; as an early access title on the first of June. In some ways, calling it a game is overstating it: it's little more than a collection of programming problems, with a little story to give it some structure. The catch is that you're programming in an assembly language on a virtual machine with unusual architecture; problems beyond the simplest will generally require you to take advantage of parallelism (which is the primary distinguishing feature of the VM), resulting in novel solutions for ordinary problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="TIS-100 game screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/370360_2015-06-17_00005.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, a game like that has a rather limited target audience. Case in point: I have myself previously created a little VM with a fake assembly language to play with. The game is clearly made just for me, but how many others are likely to be similarly interested? About 11,000,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; so far. It's a minor hit.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of programming as gameplay isn't new. Indeed, Zachtronics's earlier game, &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;, is also an exercise in parallel programming, though dressed up in fancier clothes. Way back in the mists of time,&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;Robot Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; challenged players to program the titular robots to solve puzzles. And on the more-programming-than-game end of the spectrum, we have &lt;em&gt;Core War&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a multitude of web sites in the vein of &lt;a href="https://projecteuler.net/"&gt;Project Euler&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.codingame.com/home"&gt;CodinGame&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been enjoying &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;, but more than that, I think it's singularly impressive to release a game of this kind. Certainly, there are games that trade on their difficulty (&lt;em&gt;Super Hexagon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;I Wanna Be the Guy&lt;/em&gt;, etc.) and some that take pride in their difficulty of interaction (&lt;em&gt;Surgeon Simulator&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ampu-Tea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;QWOP&lt;/em&gt;, etc.), and simple 'retro-style' graphics are &lt;em&gt;de rigueur&lt;/em&gt; for indie games, but the very minimalistic functionalism of &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; is astounding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; is difficult because the thinking required to solve the puzzles is difficult. It is perhaps inaccessible, because it consists of nothing else &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the tools to solve the puzzle. Its graphics are simple because everything you need to solve the puzzles is a text-mode interactive debugger, and that's what you get. Like a sudoku puzzle or a crossword, &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; is a completely pure puzzle game: the game takes place in your head, and the software keeps score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not by chance that &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; so distinguishes itself from other games. During the production of &lt;em&gt;Infinifactory&lt;/em&gt;, Zach Barth, the founder of Zachtronics, wanted to make a game with a smaller team--something more-indie-than-indie--to get back to his roots as an indie developer. The project turned out to be too great in scope, but from its wreckage was salvaged a programming minigame which became &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Viewed as an indie developer's attempt to make something &lt;em&gt;even more indie&lt;/em&gt;, with the understanding that it was a small part of something larger, the design makes sense.&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game's manual, too, reflects the niche targeted by the game. Who reads a manual, you ask? When it is positioned as a technical document describing the instruction set of a virtual machine, the answer to that question is: programmers. The manual is presented as the in-universe manual for the TIS-100 computer, previously the property of the player character's Uncle Randy, including handwritten notes and highlighting. This was part of Zachtronics's attempt to make a game with "an irresistible value proposition. For us, that's a game with a 14-page technical manual that we designed, printed out, marked up and scanned back in again."&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:7" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The manual is reminiscent of the feelies accompanying Infocom games, among others, in years past.&lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:8" rel="footnote"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="TIS-100 results screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/370360_2015-06-18_00001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like its predecessor, &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; encourages players to perfect their solutions, optimizing for either execution speed, least number of nodes used, or least instructions--goals which are often contradictory, requiring multiple solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps unsurprisingly, given that it is a game about programming, the players of &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; have created some auxiliary tools, including &lt;a href="http://www.tis100pad.com/"&gt;TIS-100 PAD&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;sup id="fnref:9"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:9" rel="footnote"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which allows users to more easily share solutions, and a variety of TIS-100 (the virtual machine, not the game) emulators.&lt;sup id="fnref:10"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:10" rel="footnote"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this unsolicited community participation, with the release of the specification editor, which allows players to make their own puzzles, a puzzle design contest was announced. Twenty-five puzzles will be selected from the submissions for an official bonus campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feel of &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt; is both nostalgic and quite modern. It's an intriguing combination, and I recommend it to anyone still interested after hearing me call it "a collection of programming problems." Coders, no prior experience with assembly is needed. Others, if you like this game--try coding. You'll probably like that, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Barth2012]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Zach Barth, &lt;a href="http://gamasutra.com/view/feature/172250/postmortem_zachtronics_.php"&gt;Postmortem: Zachtronics Industries' &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Gamasutra (2012-06-13).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Dewdney1984]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Alexander K. Dewdney, &lt;a href="http://www.koth.org/info/akdewdney/First.htm"&gt;In the game called Core War hostile programs engage in a battle of bits&lt;/a&gt;, Scientific American &lt;strong&gt;250&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt; (1984), 15--19.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[McIlroy1971]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;M. Douglas McIlroy &amp;amp; Robert Morris &amp;amp; Victor Vyssotsky, &lt;a href="http://www.cs.dartmouth.edu/~doug/darwin.pdf"&gt;Letter to Aleph-Null&lt;/a&gt; (1971-06-29).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;[Wawro2015]&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Alex Wawro, &lt;a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/244969/Things_we_create_tell_people_who_we_are_Designing_Zachtronics_TIS100.php"&gt;'Things we create tell people who we are': Designing Zachtronics' &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Gamasutra (2015-06-09).&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://steamspy.com/app/370360"&gt;According to SteamSpy&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, it has 270 positive reviews and 2 negative reviews &lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/370360/"&gt;on Steam&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1984, actually. It was released a year later for DOS, &lt;a href="http://www.mobygames.com/game/robot-odyssey/release-info"&gt;according to MobyGames&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also from 1984, described in a Scientific American article, [Dewdney1984]. It's based on a still earlier programming game, &lt;em&gt;Darwin&lt;/em&gt;, which was played in 1961 and described publicly in 1972. See [McIlroy1971] for more.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The details of &lt;em&gt;TIS-100&lt;/em&gt;'s inception, and more, are discussed in an interview published by Gamasutra, [Wawro2015].&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Barth wrote in a post mortem of &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;, [Barth2012], that &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt; was too difficult and inaccessible. New titles were forthcoming: "New titles, I might add, that are hopefully more accessible than &lt;em&gt;SpaceChem&lt;/em&gt;!"&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From [Wawro2015].&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when you &lt;em&gt;got something&lt;/em&gt; for your money! &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/commentary/software-in-the-age-of-sneakernet-a-pictorial.html"&gt;Even application software used to have much more bulk to it&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:8" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source available &lt;a href="https://github.com/Triplanetary/tis100pad"&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:9" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just have a look at the results of &lt;a href="https://github.com/search?p=2&amp;amp;amp;q=tis-100&amp;amp;amp;type=Repositories&amp;amp;amp;utf8=%E2%9C%93"&gt;this search&lt;/a&gt;. But watch out, if you'd like to avoid spoilers! The puzzle solutions are code, after all, so a number of people have posted those, as well.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:10" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="programming game"></category><category term="Zachtronics Industries"></category><category term="puzzle"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="Windows"></category><category term="2015"></category></entry><entry><title>Bleed Out Sakuretsu</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/bleed-out-sakuretsu.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T12:53:04-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-04-05:too-much-free-time/game/bleed-out-sakuretsu.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don't believe I've written about any remotely popular games for at least two years... and I'm not about to change that. But I am writing about a good game, at least: &lt;em&gt;Bleed Out Sakuretsu&lt;/em&gt;, a vertically scrolling shooter for the Sharp X68000, by Gold Cats Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bleed Out Sakuretsu title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Bleed-Out-Sakuretsu-title.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First: yes, the title screen says 'sakuretu'. But the common romanization of this game's title seems to be 'sakuretsu', and as goes TOSEC, so goes my nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="In-game" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Bleed-Out-Sakuretsu-ingame.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bleed Out Sakuretsu&lt;/em&gt; has a powerup system reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;Gradius&lt;/em&gt;. As you continue scoring points, you can purchase a shot upgrade, a barrier, or other, even more powerful powerups. The opposition is a variety of ships, small shots, and guided missiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Boss fight" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Bleed-Out-Sakuretsu-boss.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boss sprays out bullets danmaku-style, and periodically fires a pair of front-facing lasers. You've got to deal with this while avoiding guided missiles, and since you are destroyed in one shot (unless you buy a barrier), this, like the rest of the level, provides a good challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, an unfortunate revelation: the boss is, as far as I can tell, invulnerable, because the available version of &lt;em&gt;Bleed Out Sakuretsu&lt;/em&gt; is a trial edition, and I can find no evidence that any full version was ever created. I would love to hear otherwise, if anyone has better information on old doujin games than I do, because it's a very fun game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qMZdr6LtHT8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to do a shooter justice with just words and screenshots. The video above shows (I believe) the entire game, which should give a much better picture of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like shooters, I'd say &lt;em&gt;Bleed Out Sakuretsu&lt;/em&gt; is worth a try. It's only about two minutes long, but it's fun, and I believe there's a place for brief games, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Touhou&lt;/em&gt; series looms largest on the doujin shooter landscape, of course, but there's a huge and fascinating variety of games (of all genres) stretching back decades, which I think could use some more attention from the English-speaking web. I'll probably be looking at a few more doujin games in coming weeks, so I'll try to shine a light on whichever titles catch my eye. Maybe there will be some hidden gems, or maybe just hidden failures. We'll see what comes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="doujin shooter"></category><category term="Gold Cats Project"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="vaporware"></category><category term="1996"></category><category term="x68000"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="good"></category></entry><entry><title>History Mystery</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/history-mystery.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T13:47:29-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-03-12:too-much-free-time/game/history-mystery.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the early eighties, the sudden popularity (and, indeed, the recent &lt;em&gt;existence&lt;/em&gt;) of home computers gave rise to a new kind of publication: the disk magazine. These periodicals were published not on paper but on computer disks (and sometimes cassettes), and although the content varied, they generally featured computer programs (including games) in addition to, or even in place of, articles. The most famous of these are perhaps &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Softdisk_(disk_magazine)"&gt;Softdisk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; for the Apple II (launched in 1981) and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loadstar"&gt;Loadstar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; for the Commodore 64 (launched in 1984). The medium flourished&lt;sup id="fnref:diskmags"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:diskmags" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; alongside more traditional magazines which might offer (inconvenient!) type-in programs. There was a price to be paid for this convenience: a single 'issue' of &lt;em&gt;Softdisk&lt;/em&gt; cost about the same as an annual subscription to a paper magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the many disk mags was Scholastic's &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; for Apple II. Featuring (as you might expect) primarily educational content, &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; began publication in 1983,&lt;sup id="fnref:micropub"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:micropub" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; continuing for about a decade. It also inspired a spin-off series, &lt;em&gt;Microzine Jr.&lt;/em&gt;, which was launched in 1988. Each issue of &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; included four programs, one of which was a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="History Mystery title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Microzine18.Sid_000000004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which all brings me to the subject of this article: &lt;em&gt;History Mystery&lt;/em&gt; by David A. Bowman and &lt;a href="http://www.highcastle.com/MarkHome/mark.htm"&gt;Mark A. Malamud&lt;/a&gt;, which was included in &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; #18 in November 1986. According to the '&lt;a href="https://tmft.wordpress.com/?attachment_id=945"&gt;Letter from the Editor&lt;/a&gt;' in that issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll have fun reading &lt;strong&gt;The History Mystery&lt;/strong&gt; Twistaplot™ adventure. A priceless hourglass has been stolen from the Microville History Museum. Some of the ghosts in the museum will help you find it. (Yes, the museum is haunted!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You play the part of "the ace reporter of your school newspaper, &lt;span style="text-decoration:underline;"&gt;The Chronicle&lt;/span&gt;" (incidentally, &lt;a href="https://tmft.wordpress.com/?attachment_id=953"&gt;of selectable gender&lt;/a&gt;), out to get a story about a stolen Babylonian hourglass. After chatting with the ghost of Mark Twain about the situation, you find yourself in the lobby of the museum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Museum lobby" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Microzine18.Sid_000000014.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The museum consists of 29 rooms&lt;sup id="fnref:map"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:map" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which you must navigate, gathering items and clues to solve the mystery of the stolen hourglass, which the museum's ghosts believe is actually located within the museum. Each room has a description, seen on entering the room, and an entry in the self-guided tape-recorded tour, accessed by pressing &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;. The tour often contained educational information&lt;sup id="fnref:tour"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:tour" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which might be used to solve the game's puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Age of Dinosaurs room" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Microzine18.Sid_000000019.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some rooms have items to be collected, while others have ghosts to talk to or other objects to interact with. The game is in two parts (purely for practical reasons, I presume). Selecting the second part from the menu requires the player to input the password given at the end of the first part ("The Sands of Time") and begins the second part, in which the player must collect the hourglass and escape the museum while being chased by Winsome Slugg, the criminal who had stolen it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tracy's Gift Shop" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tracys-gift-shop.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon completing the game, the player gets a rather neat reward: the museum's gift shop, called "Amy Minkley's Gift Shop",&lt;sup id="fnref:giftshop"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:giftshop" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; will be renamed after the player. Not only in the ending text, either: in future playthroughs, the in-game name is changed. Which, I suppose, might make this the first game with a New Game+ feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;History Mystery&lt;/em&gt; took me about an hour to complete, though I suppose it took me quite a bit longer when I was a child. I remember having a lot of fun with it, back then, and it's still neat as a bit of nostalgia, today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tales of Suspense" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tales-of-suspense.jpg" /&gt;
My copy of the game is this 1987 compilation, &lt;em&gt;Tales of Suspense&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll try to look at some more games from &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; and other disk mags in the future. There's a lot to be said about them, and the resources on the internet are scarce at best. This post has been several years in the making, during which time I've been contacted a number of times by people who, like me, had fond memories of a game which &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; have been &lt;em&gt;History Mystery&lt;/em&gt;, but who couldn't be sure. My thanks to them for providing me the impetus to do my civic duty and get this out there. Fans of old educational games, you are appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:diskmags"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia has &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_disk_magazines"&gt;a substantial list&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:diskmags" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:micropub"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="http://apple2history.org/history/ah21/#15"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;: "The first issue of &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt; was first displayed at the January 1983 Consumer Electronics Show, and was available in stores by March 1983.")&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:micropub" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:map"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mapped them out &lt;a href="https://tmft.wordpress.com/?attachment_id=947"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:map" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:tour"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"...Welcome to the Telephone Exhibit. The first telephone call was made by Alexander Graham Bell. As he was calling, he accidently spilled acid on himself and yelled for his assistant: 'Mr. Watson, come here. I want you!'...."&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:tour" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:giftshop"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the game, "named after one of the great school reporters" (probably the editor of your school newspaper, Amy Minkly), but likely &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; named after Amy E. McKinley, the editor of &lt;em&gt;Microzine&lt;/em&gt;--though perhaps she was a school reporter, once.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:giftshop" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="history"></category><category term="David A. Bowman"></category><category term="Mark A. Malamud"></category><category term="Microzine"></category><category term="new game plus"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="Scholastic"></category><category term="selectable gender"></category><category term="educational"></category><category term="1986"></category><category term="adventure"></category><category term="Apple II"></category><category term="good"></category></entry><entry><title>IFComp 2014: One Night Stand</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-one-night-stand.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:32:51-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-10-19:too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-one-night-stand.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The third game I've played from the 2014 ifcomp is &lt;em&gt;One Night Stand&lt;/em&gt; by Giannis G. Georgiou. You play Sandy, a woman who is trying to discover the name of the man she just spent the night with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One pre-spoiler note: the download from the comp website just has an HTML file with a link to a web-based version of the game, but the story file &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be downloaded, if you follow that link. You'll need a Quest interpreter to play it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This post contains spoilers. Read at your own risk.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a note about online play: the online interpreter was rather slow to react, occasionally taking many seconds to complete a command, and usually missing the first few characters of each command I typed, since it was still scrolling the response text. This was irritating, but it otherwise worked fine, and it was at least visually attractive. Not ideal, but better than nothing, given that I don't actually have a Quest interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;ONS&lt;/em&gt; is a short comedy game with one puzzle sequence. I spent about 35 minutes prodding everything in the game before I finished, but I imagine 10 minutes would more than suffice, if you just proceed toward the goal--and particularly if you aren't using the rather slow web-based interpreter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the customized responses to trying to take various objects, and the randomly chosen sections of text (e.g. when knocking on Mara's door) are a nice touch. The ending, though not &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; unexpected, is a good enough payoff for the few minutes the game takes to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, you don't have any real options--either you proceed linearly through the story, or you don't proceed at all. I wanted to try tricking the dude into saying his name. To break down in tears to avoid the situation. To call him Rumpelstiltskin, if his name is so important. Anything to have some choice--but I had none. More mundanely, there are few objects implemented, and no real, interactive NPCs. The parser is a little obtuse, too: you've got to &lt;strong&gt;knock door&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;use bottle on floor&lt;/strong&gt;, which aren't exactly the first commands that came to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, an average-quality game, which would probably be more at home in the first ifcomp than the twentieth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Post-review pre-posting note&lt;/em&gt;: Okay, I think this review needs an addendum. Other reviewers seem to be unanimous in despising this game. It was my assumption throughout the game that it was a work of parody--the several-inches deep layer of grease on the kitchen floor not a greater exaggeration than the PC's absurd internal monologue. &lt;em&gt;Surely&lt;/em&gt; the game is so stupid exactly because it's undermining its nominal position. Of course, while writing the review, I was under the impression that the author was a woman (Wrong! Giannis is a Greek name which is the masculine form Gianna. The more you know.), and that therefore the PC &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be a parody of the ridiculous caricatures of women we see in games and other media (maybe not?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's against my policy to change my judgment after reading other reviews, so I'll let this review stand as-is. I'd rather be too generous in my assumptions about other people than too harsh. In retrospect, though, if you take seriously the bits that I assumed to be failed comedy, then the game really &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; become rather unpalatable... so take this review with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="female protagonist"></category><category term="ifcomp 2014"></category><category term="2014"></category><category term="freeware"></category><category term="interactive fiction"></category><category term="platform independent"></category><category term="Giannis G. Georgiou"></category></entry><entry><title>IFComp 2014: Raik</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-raik.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:38:06-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-10-17:too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-raik.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The second game I'm looking at this year is &lt;em&gt;Raik&lt;/em&gt; by Harry Giles, which is written with Twine. According to the blurb, it is "A scots fantasia about anxiety. Battle kelpies, watch TV, avoid your emails and find the magical Staff of the Salmon." Sounds amusing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This post contains spoilers. Read at your own risk.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My spoiler warning above goes double for this game. Really definitely don't read this without playing the game. I mean it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you start the game, you're advised that you can "Learn about Scots and use a translator at &lt;a href="http://www.scots-online.org/"&gt;Scots-Online.org&lt;/a&gt;", and you are presented with a pair of links: &lt;strong&gt;gang&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;go&lt;/strong&gt;. It looks from the outset as if the game is simply available in two languages--Scots and English--for flavor, and the "Translate to Scots" and "Translate to English" links that appear reinforce this. The text is even very similar in shape in each language. However, this is only a facade: there are two stories being told, and they are superficially unrelated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Scots-language story, the PC struggles through the day, trying to fill time: "If ye can get tae hauf five, mebbe ye can get tae dinner, than mebbe ye can get tae bed."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the English-language story, the PC is on an epic quest: "You are searching for the Staff of the Salmon, whose magic alone will release your clan from the withering curse of Black Edward."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the bottom of each page of text is an option to 'translate' into the other language, which actually presents not a translation but the section of the story which is in the corresponding position in the other language: the stories are structurally the same. They are related in more ways that one: at the end of the English-language story, "You imagine another version of yourself, who stayed in bed that fateful day and even now lies frozen in time, unable to act, an endless scream seeking only relief." In the most recent corresponding part of the Scots-language story, the PC is paralyzed by a panic attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interpretation: the Scots-language story is 'real', and the English-language story is the PC's way of dealing with life--or of &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; dealing with life, as the case may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The duality of the stories is very cool and well done. Though you could (mostly) play them separately, the English-language story serves as commentary on the Scots-language story. For example, when the PC of the Scots-language story is (figuratively) lost in a panic attack, the PC of the English-language story is (literally) lost in a maze. It's an impressive way to use metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The individual stories are well-crafted, too. I particularly liked the use of links to pace the story. Early on, links interrupting the text make the story seem to move slower, but later they make the pacing seem more frantic--well done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll note that my praise is all for 'meta' aspects of the game--this is not an accident. The &lt;em&gt;actual game&lt;/em&gt; isn't all that interesting. The Scots-language story is dull (but it's &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be, since it's the 'real-world' part of the game) and the English-language story is far from engaging. However, the game is quite short (about fifteen minutes for a single playthrough), so this wasn't a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language aspect could prove something of a problem. It's easy enough to tell the general sense of the Scots-language story, but for most readers there will be &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; specific terms that require definition. It's certainly the author's intention to induce readers to learn more about Scots, which is fine, though I wonder how much effort the (non-comp-judging) general public will be willing to expend on comprehension. My own experience with Scots (other than &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To_a_Mouse"&gt;Robert Burns&lt;/a&gt;) is limited to an encounter with the &lt;a href="https://sco.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page"&gt;Scots Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, some years ago. At the time, I judged that the editors were treating Scots as a somewhat more dignified version of leet-speak, and put it from my mind. It &lt;a href="https://stats.wikimedia.org/EN/SummarySCO.htm"&gt;seems to have done better since&lt;/a&gt;, though it still has very few editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the author, &lt;em&gt;Raik&lt;/em&gt; was inspired by &lt;em&gt;Depression Quest&lt;/em&gt;, which I have not yet played. I'd like to come back to this game after playing &lt;em&gt;Depression Quest&lt;/em&gt;, to see how it affects my opinion. At any rate, I foresee myself continuing to revisit and think about this game in the future, which is about the highest praise that can be given to a 'serious' game like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play time: about 40 minutes for several playthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="freeware"></category><category term="interactive fiction"></category><category term="platform independent"></category><category term="Harry Giles"></category><category term="ifcomp 2014"></category><category term="mental health"></category><category term="storytelling"></category><category term="2014"></category></entry><entry><title>IFComp 2014: Hill 160</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-hill-160.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T16:43:27-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-10-17:too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2014-hill-160.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new year brings a new ifcomp. The first game, this year, is &lt;em&gt;Hill 160&lt;/em&gt; by Mike Gerwat, billed as "A World War I Adventure in Terror". This appears to be Gerwat's first comp entry, though he has released another game, &lt;em&gt;Genesis Quest&lt;/em&gt;, which is available &lt;a href="http://www.ifarchive.org/if-archive/games/glulx/GenesisQuest.ulx"&gt;on the ifarchive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This post contains spoilers. Read at your own risk.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, this first game is one I couldn't finish. The author indicates that this game has been made easier to comply with the comp rules (the two-hour rule, I suppose), but I sincerely doubt that anyone will finish the game, because the walkthrough is a bit over 700 commands long. To complete the game you'd need to execute one (correct!) command every &lt;em&gt;ten seconds&lt;/em&gt;. Judging by the walkthrough, in 48 minutes I got through about a sixth of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the game were only too long, I would have continued to play for the full two hours games are allotted. Unfortunately, the game has three crippling flaws: first, it is tedious; second, it is unfriendly (more on this later); third, it is buggy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tedium is, I presume, intentional: it's intended to reflect the tedium of war. To that end, the game involves plenty of actions that are boring, repetitive, or both. The walkthrough contains (from about 700 turns) 57 turns of waiting, 19 turns of sleeping, and 16 turns of 'again', which are mostly sleeping or waiting. When you are acting, you are often doing something like &lt;strong&gt;drop pants / crap in trench / pull up pants&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unfriendliness is the main reason I gave up. Any little thing you do that isn't according to script will generally end the game. Leave the latrine without using it? "You didn't take your shite! GAME OVER MATEY!". Walk onto the battlefield without cleaning your rifle? "You didn't clean your rifle! GAME OVER MATEY!". Try to take the supplies you're after, rather than asking for them? "GAME OVER MATEY!".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not generally obvious what you're meant to do until you've already failed. How was I to know I had to clean the rifle? It's description didn't mention anything. For that matter, how was I to know I had to attach the bayonet myself? The game over message tells me that "Your rifle is missing a critical part.", but attempting to examine it again gives me "You've already examined the rifle.". The game won't let you examine anything twice, or talk to anyone twice. If you don't have a transcript, you'd better have remembered the names of the members of your platoon--you won't be seeing them again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not always obvious how to accomplish things, either. When you're sent for supplies, trying to simply take them from the supply party gets you killed, but &lt;strong&gt;talk to party&lt;/strong&gt; gives "You can't talk to the supply party." In fact, you must &lt;strong&gt;ask party for supplies&lt;/strong&gt;. But &lt;strong&gt;talk to grant&lt;/strong&gt; worked, earlier. The requirements are inconsistent. Once, when talking to Grant, you must salute (or game over!), but later, saluting isn't necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the game is buggy. If you talk to Grant in the Main Trench before going out on the recon mission, he gives the speech that he gave earlier about you needing to go pick up supplies. Waiting repeatedly will repeatedly give the text about Grant arriving. Sometimes waiting will just do nothing with no message at all. And it's not strictly a bug, but &lt;strong&gt;take all&lt;/strong&gt; should not open up every container and fill my inventory with several screens worth of cigarettes and grenades and things. It should just pick up the items I dropped. Very irritating!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that said, the game does have its good points. The author indicates that it's intended to be fairly realistic, based on his over 40 years of study, and there are plenty of interesting details. There are some detailed descriptions of certain items, and the language and situation are (apparently--the first World War is not my forte) also intended to be realistic. For my part, I'd enjoy it more simply exploring the environment than having the game nag at me about every minor detail (and the author promises that "When it goes up on the archive, it will be much harder with Release 2." Not necessary!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hill 160&lt;/em&gt; has potential, but I won't be returning to the current release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play time: 48 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="freeware"></category><category term="2014"></category><category term="interactive fiction"></category><category term="platform independent"></category><category term="ifcomp 2014"></category><category term="Mike Gerwat"></category><category term="World War 1"></category></entry><entry><title>Hanoi (1978)</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/hanoi-1978.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T19:26:48-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2012-05-29:too-much-free-time/game/hanoi-1978.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hanoi&lt;/em&gt; by Glen Fisher, published in &lt;em&gt;Cursor&lt;/em&gt; #05 (Nov. 1978), is a Tower of Hanoi game for the Commodore PET.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/hanoi1978-1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hanoi&lt;/em&gt;, like most Tower of Hanoi games for Commodore computers, is a very simple and straightforward implementation. The rules should be familiar to most of us, but you may &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_Hanoi"&gt;see Wikipedia for details&lt;/a&gt;. In this version, you select the number of discs in the puzzle, between two and seven, and then you are prompted from which pile to pick up a disc, and onto which pile to place it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discs move with a simple but smooth animation--nice enough, I suppose, at first, but it would get very tiresome indeed in the 127 moves it takes to solve a puzzle with seven discs. Upon completion of the puzzle, the game tells you how many moves you used, and how many were required, at minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I doubt anyone will be much interested in a simple Tower of Hanoi game in any case, I'll still recommend against this particular version. It's not bad, for what it is, but it's got nothing in particular to recommend it, either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two updated versions of &lt;em&gt;Hanoi&lt;/em&gt; were released, one in 1980, and another in 1984, which included color but were otherwise similar.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1978"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="Commodore PET"></category><category term="Tower of Hanoi"></category><category term="Glen Fisher"></category></entry><entry><title>IFComp 2010: Under, In Erebus</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2010-under-in-erebus.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T19:00:38-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2010-10-21:too-much-free-time/game/ifcomp-2010-under-in-erebus.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Under, In Erebus&lt;/em&gt; by Brian Rapp is an interactive fiction game entered in the 2010 interactive fiction competition. You've accidentally boarded the wrong train, and when it stops, you're in a dark and unusual place. How will you get home?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This post contains spoilers. Read at your own risk.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt; is severely under-hinted. I solved very few of the puzzles without using the hints. Actually, I didn't even figure out that the booths were used for spelling out objects until I read the hints. It wasn't even entirely clear that you &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; trying to escape. For all I knew, you were supposed to make friends with the cyclops and learn his secret of eternal life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the puzzles felt positively obtuse. Spelling out PUB in order to get a drink? Was there some hint that I missed? Making a cup and a tub were pretty obvious, but that's pretty much all I managed alone. And the ending puzzle is absolutely impossible to guess, as far as I can tell. "You could use some assistance in escaping from Erebus. A student who will follow your instructions would be ideal." Why would I even consider that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some other problems, too. It was necessary to repeatedly travel around collecting ingredients (or, rather, letters) to try out puzzle solutions. Every time I needed a pea I had to go get one, open the pod, then use it. Eventually I just collected a big stack of bees and peas and dropped them near the booths, but I still had to make trips for the tea, ewes, and eye. I get that, from an in-game perspective, there should only be one eye at a time (though it reappearing sort of ruins that), but there could have been a whole flock of sheep I could herd to the booths, and I could have poured a small amount of tea out of the tub, leaving it little diminished. It was also a pain to have to take things out of the pack repeatedly. I'm of the opinion that if there's no good reason to restrict the player's inventory size, you shouldn't do it--I believe players will forgive at least that failure of realism in service to playability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt; wasn't all bad, though: there were some nice responses; the various 'bonus' words you could make were amusing--though not amusing enough to make me want to make them all, given the painfully large amount of work involved in making just one word; the changes in the response to examining yourself were nice; the fact that the backpack became a wristpack was a nice bit of attention to detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess there were some things I didn't explore. I couldn't work out how to explore the pit, though the ten points I got for making it would seem to indicate there's more to it. Maybe I should have tried "TILT"? But it's too late now, and I don't think I'll ever go back to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I regret that &lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt;'s shortcomings so outweighed its successes. The environment seemed like it might be fun, and I do enjoy wordplay--&lt;em&gt;Ad Verbum&lt;/em&gt; is one of my favorite games. But everything I did in &lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt; just felt like slow work. With better hinting and an easier way to create the words, &lt;em&gt;Erebus&lt;/em&gt; could be a pretty solid game. As it stands, though, it's just more trouble than it's worth.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="2010"></category><category term="interactive fiction"></category><category term="platform independent"></category><category term="Brian Rapp"></category><category term="fantasy"></category><category term="ifcomp 2010"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="wordplay"></category></entry><entry><title>The Wizard's Castle</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/the-wizards-castle.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T18:51:22-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2010-02-23:too-much-free-time/game/the-wizards-castle.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Wizard's Castle&lt;/em&gt;, published for DOS in 1981 by International PC Owners is an early dungeon crawl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Intro" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/castle_000.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoiding the word 'year'? Check. Awesome apostrophes? Check. Journey from which no adventurer has ever returned? Yep! Let's make a journey to the cave of cliches! Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cliched-and-basically-nonexistent plot aside, &lt;em&gt;The Wizard's Castle&lt;/em&gt; is actually a pretty solid game. You start by choosing some basic stats for your character (race, sex, strength/intelligence/dexterity, equipment), and off you go to explore the castle and hunt for the incredible *ORB OF ZOT*. You're aided in your endeavour by a map of the dungeon which is meant to fill in as you explore or use items that reveal information about the dungeon, like flares or the lamp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Map" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/castle_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in the version I played, the map is already filled in, which I guess is a bug; I'm told later ports give you a properly blank map to start with. One annoying thing about this game is that the map legend is on the help screen, so you have to keep switching between the map and legend until you learn the meaning of the map symbols. Similarly, the player's stats are only shown upon moving into a room, so you have to move around to check them. There is plenty of room on the right for both of these, I think. Another, more minor problem is that you must press 'M' whenever you wish to show the map; since that is likely to be all the time, it means that the game consists of lots of &lt;code&gt;EMSMEEM&lt;/code&gt;, manually checking the map every few moves. It would have benefited greatly from just automatically showing the map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map issues aside, how is the game? Well, let's have a look at the map: the player is on the square marked by angle brackets above; to the west is a monster; to the east is a sinkhole, which drops the player down a level; to the south is a flare, which would ordinarily be very useful, as it lights up the area around the player, but is, in this version, useless due to the map being all filled in. Monsters can be fought, fled from, or bribed, though some (trolls, ogres, dragons) don't seem to be damaged by the sword I had, so it may be impossible to (successfully) fight some of them. Sinkholes cause the player to fall down a level, and stairs can lead either up or down. Items, such as flares, gold, and treasure, will be picked up automatically, and can be used or (in the case of gold and treasure) traded with the vendors the player will encounter in the dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successfully navigating the dungeon involves carefully planning your route, lest you find yourself very dead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Dead again" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/castle_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all fights should be avoided, though. With the lamp, it's possible to tell precisely what monster is in an adjacent square, and the weaker ones can be fought for large sums of gold, which is very handy. However, it's not only the fights that can be hazardous: magic pools can be drunk from, and may either help or harm the player, and books, too,  can be either very helpful or very dangerous--even the chests might explode or release toxic gas upon being opened. After picking up some treasures, the player can choose to leave the dungeon, or continue on, seeking the ultimate treasure in the form of the Orb of Zot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking the Orb of Zot is harder than it sounds. Scattered about are orbs the player can gaze into in order to gain information about what lies in the dungeon--these will occasionally tell the player that the Orb of Zot is in some particular location, but this isn't as helpful as it seems--the orbs may claim that the Orb is in several different locations, and I have yet to find it by going to these locations. I suspect there is a trick to it, but I've not spent enough time to puzzle it out. For now, I'm satisfied with picking up the lesser treasures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DYWYPI?" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/castle_004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dungeon is randomized each time you play, so if you care to, you can play as many times as you like without running out of new dungeons to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom line: &lt;em&gt;The Wizard's Castle&lt;/em&gt; is pretty fun. I'm sure it would have been much more challenging to collect the treasures if the map had functioned correctly in the version I played, so I suspect this game would be good for a few hours distraction here and there. There's something satisfying about a nice dungeon crawl, and for all its simplicity and lack of polish, &lt;em&gt;The Wizard's Castle&lt;/em&gt; isn't bad at all. It's no Nethack, but it's worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1981"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="dungeon crawl"></category><category term="RPG"></category><category term="fantasy"></category><category term="International PC Owners"></category><category term="Joseph R. Power"></category></entry><entry><title>Phage Wars 2</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/phage-wars-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-01T19:08:25-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2009-08-22:too-much-free-time/game/phage-wars-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.kongregate.com/games/ArmorGames/phage-wars-2/?referrer=Sopoforic"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phage Wars 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Armor Games is a fun little flash game, though not a terribly difficult one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Main screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/phagewars2-snap113.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Phage Wars 2, the player is a lab tech whose goal is to create the most powerful virus ever. This is accomplished by playing through the 32 stages (called 'experiments') and adding the gene proteins you discover to your virus in order to improve its strength, speed, defense, agility, and ability to reproduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Beginning an experiment" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/phagewars2-snap115.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the 32 experiments contains a number of cells and enemy viruses. The player can choose to infect cells or attack cells which are already infected by an enemy virus in order to take them over. Once a cell is infected, the virus inside begins to reproduce, so the player can then attack other cells. The stage is won when no enemy viruses remain. A new gene protein is discovered after beating each stage for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/phagewars2-snap118.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between experiments, the player has the opportunity to add the gene proteins to his virus. The proteins have varying effects, and can increase some statistics while decreasing others. Additionally, each protein takes up a certain amount of space in the virus's genetic code, so the player must choose between them to create the strongest virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Upgrading a virus" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/phagewars2-snap119.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The controls are pretty simple: click and drag from a source cell to a destination cell to send your viruses to infect or attack. To send viruses from multiple cells to a single destination, just drag over all the desired source cells. The best strategy I found was to infect as many cells as possible as quickly as possible, and then to attack the enemy viruses once all the empty cells had been claimed. To support this, I improved the attack, defense, and reproductive ability of my virus, though I understand that improving speed and agility is also a valid strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here lies the problem with the game: it's really much too easy. With a decent bonus to reproduction, the viruses will fill a cell quite quickly, and with a decent bonus to attack, it's not hard to destroy any enemy virus given a mostly-full source cell. The game requires a little juggling to make sure you maintain control of your cells, but it's not really hard to do, and by improving defense even that becomes very easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phage Wars 2&lt;/em&gt; has basically identical gameplay to its predecessor, with the exception of the ability to add proteins to improve your virus rather than simply choosing a virus at the beginning. The idea isn't totally original to this series, either--the concept is basically just &lt;em&gt;Risk&lt;/em&gt;, and the game's particulars are rather reminiscent, to me, of the primordial soup subgame in &lt;em&gt;The Time Warp of Dr. Brain&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of difficulty and originality aren't really so bad that they ruin the game; it still pretty fun. To be honest, I'm not sure I know any way to make the game more difficult without also making it frustrating or otherwise less fun. As for the originality--well, some ideas are reused because they work, and I'd say this is one of them. Give the game a shot if you've got the time to spare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gameplay: 7/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The controls are nice, the mechanics are understandable, the concept is solid. It's a little too easy, though, and the main skill required, I think, is clicking and dragging &lt;em&gt;very quickly&lt;/em&gt; at the beginning.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Story: 2/5&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The story's just an excuse for the gameplay, so this only counts half. On the other hand, the story's obviously just an excuse, so minus some points.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Graphics: 9/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The graphics are polished and lovely. Minus a point since the foreground and background were sometimes hard to distinguish, and there was nothing that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; impressed me.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Audio: 5/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;There's nothing really wrong with the audio, but it didn't stand out in any way. Some more interesting audio might have made my interest in the game last a bit longer.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Personal Slant: 6/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I enjoyed the game, though I think the sequencing part was a little dull, and the lack of difficulty made it drag on a little by the end.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Total: 6.4/10&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phage Wars 2&lt;/em&gt; is worth a play, though not a replay. In fact, I'd say that the moment you begin to become bored with it, you should abandon it--it's just more of the same, and the ending isn't worth plodding through the game if you're not enjoying it. It only takes a few minutes to play through the first few levels, though, and those few minutes are worth it.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;</summary><category term="freeware"></category><category term="2009"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="flash"></category><category term="strategy"></category><category term="Armor Games Inc."></category><category term="interesting interface"></category></entry><entry><title>Tetris</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/tetris.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-30T22:02:45-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-10-28:too-much-free-time/game/tetris.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt;, the classic falling blocks game, was released by Nintendo in November 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly, &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt; needs no introduction. There are hundreds of implementations of this simple, yet challenging game. Nintendo's 1989 offering for the NES is quite well-done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Menu" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are few options. The player can choose between A-type and B-type games, and select which music should be played, if any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Play begins" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The A-type game is simply pieces falling endlessly, with the goal being to obtain the highest score. The six types of pieces fall starting at the top of the screen, and proceed toward the bottom. While they are in the air, the player can move them left and right, rotate them, or cause them to drop more quickly. Some of the pieces are rarer than others, so it's necessary to choose where the pieces are placed with care--you can't count on a line appearing whenever you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Play continues" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_005.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every ten lines you complete, the game's speed increases one level and the colors of the blocks change. The more lines you eliminate at once, the more points you get, with a Tetris (four lines removed) scoring the most points. You also score more points if you're at a higher level--each line is worth ten times as much at level nine as it is at level zero, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="About to lose" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_008.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the game progresses and the blocks fall faster, the game becomes much more difficult. If the blocks reach too high on the screen, the music will speed up as a warning. If the blocks reach the top of the screen, you lose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="B-type game" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The B-type game is similar to the A-type game, except that rather than playing endlessly, the goal is to remove 25 lines at a particular level, and with a set height of blocks added at the start. Now the lines count down, and the game ends upon removing all 25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="B-type complete" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_007.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're given a score based on the level and height you selected, as well as the points accumulated while removing the lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="High score" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tetris_009.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your score is high enough, you can enter your name on the high score table, and be known far and wide as a Tetris master--at least until you power off the console. I played this game a lot when I was younger, though I suppose I wasn't that skilled at it--on a good game, I'd get about 110 lines, though I understand that experts can get over 200.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though this is a fairly old game, it's quite nice. The graphics are nice, clear, and colorful (though the color schemes for some of the levels are a bit ugly), the music is good, and the gameplay is simply excellent. The B-type game offers a nice, quick challenge if you're in the mood, and the A-type is nice for slightly longer gaming sessions. Of course, there are many other versions of Tetris, which may be better or worse than this one (I hear that Tengen's NES version is superior), but Nintendo's &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt; is definitely worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Gameplay&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;10/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Graphics&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;8/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Sound/Music&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;8/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Personal Slant&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;10/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Overall&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;9/10&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;</summary><category term="NES"></category><category term="1989"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="falling blocks"></category><category term="Nintendo"></category></entry><entry><title>Pinball</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/pinball.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-27T06:40:04-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-10-27:too-much-free-time/game/pinball.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pinball&lt;/em&gt; was released by Nintendo in February 1984 in Japan and October 1985 in the US, and, as the name suggests, is a simple pinball game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pinball title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Pinball_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pinball&lt;/em&gt; features two pinball screens and a bonus screen. An extra ball is awarded for every 50,000 points, and the flipper becomes invisible while your score is between 100,000 and 150,000 points. Each screen has a way to place a block post between the flippers to prevent your ball from falling, and several special ways to get large amounts of points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pinball upper screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Pinball_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After releasing the plunger, the ball goes to the top screen, and falls through one of the three lanes to score 500 or 1,000 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting the ball through the green lane on the right causes the penguins in the center to act like a slot machine, and hitting the moving pink slot target will cause them to stop on either 3, 7, or a penguin. Matching them scores points and causes a block post to appear between the flippers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting the ball through the upper left lane causes the seals to bounce balls on their noses, activating the 100 point bumper in the middle. Between this and the dots filling that lane, this scores 2,800 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The counter at the upper left awards the shown number of points when it is hit, increasing each time by 100 points, up to a maximum of 1,000 points. It resets when you put the ball through the left lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The four targets on the left award a 1,000 point bonus when you hit them all. The hole on the lower right only kicks the ball back if you fall in it; the ball exits from that hole when leaving the bonus screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Falling from the top screen doesn't lose the ball, but rather drops it to the bottom screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pinball lower screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Pinball_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bottom screen, there are a few features of note. Passing through the lanes at the top flips over the cards. When all the cards are flipped, a 5,000 point bonus is awarded, and a block post appears between the flippers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitting all seven of the targets on the left awards a 1,000 point bonus, and removes the pink bars on the right, allowing you to relaunch the ball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three eggs above the flippers hatch when hit once, disappear when hit again, and turn back to eggs when you pass over them a third time. Causing all three eggs to be hatched at the same time adds stoppers to the outlanes. Between this and the cards, it is possible to keep the ball quite safe, though these stoppers do disappear once they are hit once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the hole in the upper right leads to the bonus stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pinball bonus screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Pinball_006.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the bonus stage, you control Mario. You're supposed to run beneath the ball to bounce it back up, rather like breakout. Unlike breakout, though, the floor beneath the girl shrinks when the column of lights beneath it are turned the same color. The colors change whenever the ball rolls over them. When the floor disappears, the girl falls, and you must catch her and allow her to walk off to the left or right. Doing so awards you 10,000 points and restarts the bonus level. The level ends if the ball falls to the sides, which causes it to pop out of the hole on the top screen, or the girl falls without you catching her, which will cost you your ball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the whole game! The difference between the A and B games is that the ball is heavier in the B games, making them more challenging. It's a fairly simple game, but it's pretty well done. The controls are pretty good and the graphics aren't bad. There's no music in the game, but the sound effects are nice. I'd say that if you like pinball games, this one is worth a try. It lacks the accurate physics and detail of later pinball games, but it's still a fun diversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gameplay: 8/10
Graphics: 7/10
Sound/Music: 6/10
Personal Slant: 8/10
Overall: 7.25/10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(An &lt;a href="http://joz3d.net/documents/Pinball.txt"&gt;FAQ by Luke Jozwiak&lt;/a&gt; provided the details on the point values.)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="good"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="pinball"></category><category term="Nintendo"></category><category term="1984"></category></entry><entry><title>SkyRoads</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/skyroads.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-25T03:46:31-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-07-16:too-much-free-time/game/skyroads.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SkyRoads&lt;/em&gt; was a driving game released in 1993 by Bluemoon Interactive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkyRoads title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/skyroads_000.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The object is to complete each road, passing through the pipe at the end. There are various obstacles along the way, including blocks or gaps that must be jumped over, pipes that must be entered or avoided, as well as the threat of running out of oxygen or fuel before the end of the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkyRoads gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/skyroads_002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early roads are quite easy, requiring little jumping. Each can be completed on the first play through with minimal difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkyRoads gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/skyroads_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the game progresses, though, the roads become more difficult, some requiring multiple tries to complete. This could be a good or a bad thing, depending on your perspective. Sometimes, pipes hide walls or missing sections of floor, which will kill you, so you must remember to avoid those pipes the next time through. In my opinion, since the levels are so short (each requiring less than one minute), this required repetition does not detract from the gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SkyRoads gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/skyroads_004.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SkyRoads&lt;/em&gt; has nice graphics, and very nice music as well, together with fun gameplay--the makings of a great game. It does fall short on replay value, though. While the roads are still nice after you've beaten them, there's no real incentive to play them again--no way to try to beat your best times (which wouldn't really matter, since most roads will be completed at maximum speed anyway), no secrets to be found, and only one way through the road, with minor variations. Despite this fault, though, &lt;em&gt;SkyRoads&lt;/em&gt; is well worth playing, even if you might not play it much after you've completed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below you'll find a video of the first three roads, Red Heat, being completed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gheKz3pK7u0&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SkyRoads&lt;/em&gt; can be &lt;a href="http://www.bluemoon.ee/history/skyroads/"&gt;downloaded for free from Bluemoon Interactive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="freeware"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="1993"></category><category term="driving"></category><category term="Bluemoon Interactive"></category><category term="futuristic"></category><category term="liberated games"></category></entry><entry><title>The Adventures of Bayou Billy</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/the-adventures-of-bayou-billy.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-30T19:00:39-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-03-16:too-much-free-time/game/the-adventures-of-bayou-billy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Adventures of Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; is a beat-em-up, with a driving and shooting game thrown in for variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; won't be winning any awards for its plot. Some bad guy has kidnapped your girlfriend, and you have to rescue her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Intro" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He's even kind enough to let you know that you will be encountering obstacles on your way to his estate. What a nice guy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game behaves pretty much like your bog standard beat-em-up, with a button for punch and one for kick, and pressing both together doing a flying kick. You can pick up weapons that you knock out of your enemies' hands and to use against them. The difference, though, is that &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. It's not so bad against one enemy, but you'll find yourself fighting against three at a time, who are not stunned when you hit them, take many hits to kill, and are fairly quick-moving as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fighting three enemies" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_15.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, they are also fairly stupid, and will happily walk around in circles without hitting you, if you move just a bit. They also occasionally drop food, which heals you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans aren't your only foes, though. You'll also encounter crocodiles in the water, which are quick moving and can attack you when you're near the water's edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Crocodiles" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_17.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got to the right side of this screen, it didn't scroll any further, and since I couldn't seem to harm the crocodile, I quickly died.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Game over" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_18.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game does include, as I mentioned, a driving subgame and a shooting subgame, which can be accessed from the practice menu, and apparently appear as levels later in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Driving game" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_23.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Shooting game" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/adventures-of-bayou-billy_21.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither of these subgames was anything spectacular, although the shooting game did have the benefit of being playable with or without a zapper. Nice, since the emulated zapper uses the mouse, and playing with my laptop's touchpad was very difficult indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Adventures of Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; was called &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt; in Japan, and was considerably easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mad City title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/mad-city_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My feeling from playing a few minutes is that the enemies died in about a third as many hits in &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt;. Furthermore, the screen that wouldn't go anywhere in &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt; and had only crocodiles had divers in &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt;, and continued once I defeated them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mad City gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/mad-city_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No crocodiles in &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt;. Perhaps I didn't step on a trigger or something while playing &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt;, which caused the divers not to appear. Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I think that &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt; is probably better than &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt;, although I only played either one for a few minutes. My final opinion is that &lt;em&gt;Mad City&lt;/em&gt; is worth playing, but I'd avoid &lt;em&gt;Bayou Billy&lt;/em&gt;, since its difficulty is just not fun.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="NES"></category><category term="beat 'em up"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="Konami"></category><category term="1988"></category><category term="1989"></category></entry><entry><title>Donkey</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/donkey.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T14:23:11-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2008-01-01:too-much-free-time/game/donkey.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After far too long a break, a new game. Or, rather, quite an old one: Donkey, written in 1981 by Bill Gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DONKEY.BAS title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/donkeyqb_000.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donkey was written&lt;sup id="fnref:wp"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:wp" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as a way to showcase the capabilities of the BASIC programming language which shipped with new IBM PCs. Therefore one might expect it to be a very simple game--and simple it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/donkeyqb_001.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The object is to avoid the donkeys in the road as you drive. The controls consist of only a single button, the space bar, which is used to switch lanes. Each time you successfully pass a donkey, your car moves a bit closer to the top of the screen, so that it will be more difficult to switch in time to miss the next one. If you hit a donkey, the donkeys are given a point, you explode, and you start over:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Game Over" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/donkeyqb_003.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every eleventh donkey that you pass, you are reset to the center of the screen and given a point. The game keeps track of the score, but there's no particular reward for reaching any certain score; the game just continues until you exit. As simple and unrewarding as this game is, that's likely to be fairly soon after starting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: I've added a video demonstrating the gameplay below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7QL3yyYJ3Y&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the game &lt;a href="http://drivey.com/DONKEYQB.BAS.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:wp"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Wikipedia, which has &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DONKEY.BAS"&gt;a lengthy article&lt;/a&gt;, if you'd like to read more.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:wp" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="1981"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="DOS"></category><category term="driving"></category><category term="Bill Gates"></category></entry><entry><title>Abadox: The Deadly Inner War</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/game/abadox-the-deadly-inner-war.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-27T00:17:11-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-12-08:too-much-free-time/game/abadox-the-deadly-inner-war.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A shooter this time, and a pretty good one, at that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this game incorporates powerups, you begin, as in most similar games, with nothing but a pathetic little pea-shooter and no armor, moving very slowly indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox beginning" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_04.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had quite a bit of difficulty dodging the shots from the--very bizarre--enemies at first, but then I got a speed powerup and a couple of options and the dodging was no longer necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After progressing through a level that looked like it was made of worms, or possibly intestines, and fighting enemies like flying mouths and eyeballs, I reached the first boss: some sort of skeletal dog with bits of flesh still clinging to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox first boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_09.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This boss just jumps around a bit while releasing a few shots, so it was no problem to kill. After defeating this boss, we proceed to the second level, which is rather like the first except in much closer quarters and with various obstacles which required dodging. At the end of this level was the second boss, a face made of intestines, with its eyes floating about in front of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox second boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_13.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This boss, too, was no trouble to beat, although it did destroy my options. However, after destroying this boss, the game changed from a horizontal scroller to a vertical scroller--which scrolled from bottom to top, just to make it more confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Abadox third level" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/abadox_16.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I died a bit into this level, since I had no options and some enemies are only half-destroyed by a shot. This game is much better than most of the others I've tried. I liked Super R-Type for the SNES better, but this is also a pretty good example of the genre. Worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="good"></category><category term="horizontal scrolling shooter"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="Dynamic Planning Inc."></category><category term="ITL Co. Ltd."></category><category term="Natsume Co. Ltd."></category><category term="1989"></category></entry></feed>