<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Too Much Free Time</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/feeds/impressions.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/</id><updated>2015-06-22T00:14:56-04:00</updated><entry><title>First Impressions: Palamedes</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-palamedes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-22T00:14:56-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-25:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-palamedes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A rather fun &lt;em&gt;Tetris&lt;/em&gt;-like game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Palamedes title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Palamedes_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Palamedes isn't quite the usual falling blocks game. Instead, rows of blocks approach and it is your task to remove them by hitting them with matching block. You select which block to throw at them (from a cycle of six) and try to keep up. It's something like Bust-a-Move, I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Palamedes gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Palamedes_11.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few false starts, I made it to stage six. This one would probably be easier using a gamepad, but mine's loaned out, so take the apparent difficulty with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: It's a good game. These are few and far between, so I'd check this one out if you're a fan of falling blocks games.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="falling blocks"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="Hot-B Co. Ltd."></category><category term="Natsume Co. Ltd."></category><category term="1990"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Bump'n'Jump</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-bumpnjump.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-21T23:57:54-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-25:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-bumpnjump.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's a driving game, of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bump'n'Jump title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japanese version was called Buggy Popper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bump'n'Jump title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/buggy-popper_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start with a car driving away, with someone crying "Help me!" inside. Being the heroic gamers that we are, this is sufficient motivation for us to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Help me!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of the game seems to be that we have a car which can jump at will, and we like to land on other cars and destroy them for no reason. Well, except that it gets us points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Jumping car" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_09.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever designed these roads needs to be shot. Apparently in the bizarro-world that this game take place in, cars normally have the ability to jump (but only yours does, as far as I saw), so in order to save some of the cost of roads, they just left out some sections. Yeah, that's logical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Road, interrupted" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_13.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, we can forgive some strangeness if it's a good game, right? Of course we can. Unfortunately, the designers decided to take all of my good will and stomp on it, by putting in a ludicrously long repair sequence when you drive over one of the bonuses on the road:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Repair sequence" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_15.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You sit at this screen for upwards of fifteen seconds while text flashes on screen assuring you that they are repairing your car and have not, in fact, run off with your money and girlfriend to Tijuana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you finally finish the first level, you are treated to the second level, in which the brilliant road designer decided that if there wasn't any water to break up the monotony, then we'd just have to build some raised roads to block the lower ones instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Not a tunnel!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/bump-n-jump_21.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are helpful black areas that &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; like tunnels to pass through. They aren't. They are just there because the designer was sadistic. The problem is that if you jump any time when the little jump warning box is on the screen, you'll end up hitting the wall anyway, and it's much harder to figure out when to jump when you have to make it over a wall instead of just some water. You can't really tell how tall the thing is, since, as we all know, you should never do 3D on an NES.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we crash and die, and the game ends. I don't know what happened to that car we were chasing earlier. Probably some girl was kidnapped, and since we couldn't catch her she was raped and killed. And it's all the road designer's fault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: There are worse games. This is like a mix of Spy Hunter and Roger Rabbit, and it doesn't do well at emulating either. Play Spy Hunter instead, since it had the good sense to give you guns for killing people with, and was a better game anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="driving"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="1986"></category><category term="1988"></category><category term="Data East"></category><category term="Vic Tokai Inc."></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 3D Block</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-3d-block.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T14:11:42-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-25:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-3d-block.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A falling blocks game, which appears from the title screen to be an adult game. Is it? See inside:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="3D Block title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3d-block_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll answer now, to spare you any anxiety: if it's an adult game, no one will ever know, because it's impossible to get anything done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Starting off" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3d-block_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not too hard to rotate the shape when it's at the top, but once it gets further down it's nigh impossible to tell how it's oriented. Furthermore, it's very hard to tell at a glance what the levels below the top are like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3d-block_06.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what is that box on the lower right? Is it supposed to help me guide my blocks? It shows four blocks per level. There are sixteen blocks per level in truth. I don't know how this is meant to help, but it's about as useful as dictionary with every other letter missing--you know there's more to it, but it doesn't do you any good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all these faults, the only thing that let me complete the first level was the the blocks fall slowly--painfully slowly. You can press start to drop the block all the way, but there's no way to move it down just a bit. When the second level comes, though, this isn't a problem. Where the first level was far too slow, the second level is impossibly fast. The blocks fall completely in about a second, which is nowhere near enough time to orient them, much less position them accurately. So, we get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="About to lose" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3d-block_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the game is thankfully over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: This game shows why 3D should not be done on an NES. The 2D Tetris games are pretty good on the NES, so if you want falling blocks, play those instead.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bad"></category><category term="falling blocks"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="old 3d games"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Tenchi wo Kurau II - Shokatsu Koumei Den</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-tenchi-wo-kurau-ii-shokatsu-koumei-den.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T14:03:08-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-tenchi-wo-kurau-ii-shokatsu-koumei-den.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An RPG, and one that actually seems pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tenchi wo Kurau II title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a very lengthy opening, we find ourselves in the castle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Castle" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon leaving the building, we gain two party members, and begin to explore the town. One issue I found was that although everyone starts with equipment, it's not equipped, so you have to equip five items to each character, one at a time. An equip all feature would have been nice, but I guess you only have to do it once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Town" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_06.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Overworld" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_07.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graphics are actually pretty good for an NES game, as you see when walking around the town and then entering the world map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't play all the way through this, but it looks good so I probably will. One thing of note is that you don't have hit points in this game. Instead, you are (nominally) commanding an army, so you lose troops when attacked, and your damage is dependent on how many troops you have left. Strangely enough, though, herbs still 'heal' you and a revive still restores you to full 'health.' Possibly the designers weren't thinking it through very carefully. The battle screen is reminiscent of Final Fantasy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Battle" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/tenchi-wo-kurau-ii_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you win battles, you gain experience, and your army levels up. You gain some kind of skills, but I haven't played enough to see what they do yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: This seems like a good game. The graphics are nice and the battle system, while simple, is reasonably good. If it continues as it has begun, this game will probably be worth playing through.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="good"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="rpg"></category><category term="ancient China"></category><category term="Capcom"></category><category term="fan translation"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Tasac</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-tasac.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T12:17:36-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-tasac.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tasac is a vertical scrolling shooter by Sachen, and it sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tasac title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Tasac_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title screen looks pretty cool, so one might expect the game to have decent graphics, or something. Most of your in-game time is spent in a position like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tasac gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Tasac_04.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no real challenge in this part, except that the laser-like weapon you start with sucks, and the upgrades suck even more. When you get to the end, the boss appears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tasac pre-boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Tasac_07.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can't kill it yet. In fact, you can fly right over it. Why is the boss there before you're able to interact with it? I don't know. But the game carries on just as if the boss weren't there. In fact, it carries on the same way even once you can fight the boss--the random enemies keep appearing, there's just a boss on the screen at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tasac boss fight" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Tasac_09.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the boss shoots a pretty large number of projectiles at you, they're not hard to dodge. If the weapon weren't so stupidly slow and hard to use, they boss wouldn't be even slightly difficult. As it is, the boss just takes a little longer than it ought to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second level was just like the first. I think that the boss was slightly rounder, but I don't really care to recall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Pointless. It's just a below average vertical scroller.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bad"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="futuristic"></category><category term="not on mobygames"></category><category term="Sachen"></category><category term="Thin Chen"></category><category term="1992"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Text Editor</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-text-editor.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T11:58:27-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-text-editor.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Original title: ""РЕДАКТОР ТЕКСТОВ"". In Latin characters: "REDAKTOR TEKSTOV".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broken, probably. I'm not sure what it's supposed to do, but it just shows several screens of text then loops. Nestopia complains about bad header info, or something. The first and last screens are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Text Editor first screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Text-Editor_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Text Editor last screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Text-Editor_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: According to the &lt;a href="http://bootleggames.wikia.com/wiki/A._Chudov#.D0.A0.D0.B5.D0.B4.D0.B0.D0.BA.D1.82.D0.BE.D1.80_.D1.82.D0.B5.D0.BA.D1.81.D1.82.D0.B0_.28Text_Editor.29"&gt;BootlegGames Wiki&lt;/a&gt;, this program needs a printer. I wasn't aware that such a thing existed, but apparently some Famiclones had a printer port. The more you know!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="unplayable"></category><category term="nes"></category><category term="1996"></category><category term="A. Chudov"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: Flying Warriors</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-flying-warriors.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T11:32:35-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-flying-warriors.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yeah, it's out of order. I hit 'random game I haven't played' and I got this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Flying Warriors title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flying Warriors. It sounds like some kind of shooter maybe. Airplane game. That's cool, I liked 1943. So, what do I get? Castlevania if it sucked and had a boring training sequence. But before training, some important wisdom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Advice" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, on to the training. Since the designers went to all the trouble of putting in training, this game must have some complex controls, or something. Let's see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_20.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_05.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_22.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_06.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Controls" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, that's right. Toward automatically blocks at the right level, and B automatically punches at the right level. You get to practice these complex manoeuvres several times before you grasp them fully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Success!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_09.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes! I am a master! I can now go out and make the world a better place! But, first, a practice match against sensei. Well, sure. I'm a master now. Piece of cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fight with sensei" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_10.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we fight and... he beats me down. Badly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Have you no pride!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_11.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it's back to training. Never mind that training couldn't possibly help me, and that a monkey could manage these controls. So, we train again, he declares me a master again, we fight again, I lose again. Repeat. Repeat...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I win. So we get a scene change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rick is alone in the mountains as usual." src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_12.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Empty screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_13.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the game begins with an exciting... empty screen! I have to move off it to an entirely different scene to get to the actual game. What was the point? Why waste my time putting this scene in if there's nothing here? The next scene is some kind of mountain area, which kind of matches with the description, but that does not explain what the point of this last scene was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_15.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after that painfully long training and practice fight, we expect challenge, yes? But the enemies all die in one hit! The hardest part is managing the movement controls, since it seems to be impossible to make Rick (our hero) jump the way you want him to. After a couple of screens full of these zombie-like wimps, we enter a cave, filled with more of the same, as well as the far more dangerous bottomless pits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pits?" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_17.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, these pits are so much more dangerous, that they even kill the enemies, who just jump off like lemmings. But, remember how I said that jumping correctly was the hardest part?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pits!" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/Flying-Warriors_18.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I too jump off like a lemming. The game tells me that Rick doesn't let this stop him. Fortunately, it does stop me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: You can't skip the long intro, you have to go through boring training and practice fights, only to get to a game that acts like a bad rip off of Castlevania. Better to leave this one alone.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1990"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="beat 'em up"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="Culture Brain Inc."></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: The 3-D Battles of World Runner</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-the-3-d-battles-of-world-runner.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T11:23:05-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-the-3-d-battles-of-world-runner.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Run around, avoiding the enemies, until you get to the boss. Then button mash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="World Runner title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3-D-Battles-of-World-Runner_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's kind of dull, since all there is to do is move forward, at varying rates of speed, and jump. You get a rocket, which actually looks like a pink fireball when you use it, but I can't imagine what it's good for since any enemy you hit with the rocket wouldn't have been there when you actually run past it, and the enemies which weren't in your line of fire will run into you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="World Runner gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3-D-Battles-of-World-Runner_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to jump over some pits as you go. Since the game doesn't have real 3D, you can't really tell how wide the pits are until you're in the air, so you have to try to land in the right spot by changing speed in the air. Sometimes you have only a small area to land, so I kept overshooting or actually smacking my face on the edge of the ground and then sliding down to my death. When you finish the level you fight this centipede-thing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="World Runner boss" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/3-D-Battles-of-World-Runner_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a picture from before the game starts, since I neglected to take a screenshot while actually fighting it. Suffice to say you fire the pink rocket-fireballs at it until it dies. I have no clue how it is intended to hurt you, since it doesn't seem to have any rockets of its own. Or arms. Or anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second level is like the first, except grey. I assume that the others follow suit. The game also has an anaglyph 3D mode, activated by pressing select. I have not yet mustered the courage to try this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: It's not bad, but it wouldn't hold my attention for long.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1987"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="anaglyph 3d"></category><category term="Acclaim"></category><category term="Disk Original Group"></category><category term="Square Co. Ltd."></category><category term="old 3d games"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 1991 Du Ma Racing</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1991-du-ma-racing.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-20T11:12:10-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1991-du-ma-racing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's horse racing. The title screen greets us, for some reason, with some weird balloon horse things bouncing around:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1991 Du Ma Racing title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1991-Du-Ma-Racing_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the balloon horses were supposed to liven the game up. If so, they failed. There are two modes: race mode and gamble mode. I didn't want to contemplate what might cause you to want to bet on a race controlled by the computer with no real rewards, so I chose race mode. Presumably, it was intended for two players, but it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1991 Du Ma Racing gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1991-Du-Ma-Racing_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the little bars with the red balls near them, at the bottom? Those balls were bouncing up and down, and the object was (I deduced) to hit B when yours crossed the center line. Sort of like DDR. Even granted you could find someone else bored enough to play this game, it would be pointless, since it's all but impossible &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to hit the button at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only is this the only apparent 'challenge' in the game, it goes on forever. You have to go all the way around the track hitting B every half second or so, and that's it. The view switches to overhead when you're on the side of the track, but that doesn't matter since it's still exactly the same worthless game it was when the view was side-on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Don't bother.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1991"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="gambling"></category><category term="horse racing"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="Idea-Tek Inc."></category><category term="Super Mega"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 1944</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1944.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T22:00:27-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1944.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's a pirate version of &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1943-the-battle-of-midway.html"&gt;1943&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1944 title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1944_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only change that I noted between this and 1943 is that holding down the fire button, rather than charging the weapon, yields a very fast auto-fire. Otherwise, identical:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1944 gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1944_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Play 1943 instead.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="NES"></category><category term="pirate game"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="World War 2"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 1943 - The Battle of Midway</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1943-the-battle-of-midway.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T21:28:02-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1943-the-battle-of-midway.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An excellent conversion of Capcom's vertical scrolling shooter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1943 title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one has more features than &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1942.html"&gt;its predecessor&lt;/a&gt;, such as the ability to configure your plane before you start:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1943 customization" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_02.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, when you start, it tells you briefly what your target is. In the first level, it's Rikaku, the Japanese Heavy Cruiser:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1943 target" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is 1942, you're piloting a P-38, which you can improve as you play by picking up better weapons and energy bonuses. The gameplay is the same, too: fire at the enemy planes (and ships) while avoiding being hit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1943 ingame" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_04.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the level, you fight Rikaku, which is heavily armed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rikaku" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1943-The-Battle-of-Midway_08.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you win, you move on to the next level. There are a total of 24 levels in the NES version, as compared to 16 in the arcade version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: 1943 has excellent sound, good graphics, smooth controls, and addictive gameplay. Definitely worth playing.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1988"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="Capcom"></category><category term="World War 2"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 10-Yard Fight</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-10-yard-fight.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T20:06:29-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-10-yard-fight.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's an American football game. I don't know the rules of the game, but, honestly, I doubt that matters for this game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="10-Yard Fight title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/10-Yard-Fight_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start the game running down the field, and quickly meet the opposing team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="10-Yard Fight gameplay" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/10-Yard-Fight_03.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scene repeats, with the referee running out every few seconds, since I'm tackled every time I move. I don't think there are any controls except 'throw ball before running' and 'run.' Once I mastered this fiendishly clever control scheme, it was just a matter of seeing whether my patience or the field ran out first. It turns out that my patience won, so I got the joy of getting to the end--then starting again! Pathetic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little searching tells me that if I had been willing to spend a half hour playing this game, I'd have gotten to play defense as well as offense. Fortunately, everyone seems to agree that it's be stupid to waste that much time on this one, so I'll bow to the wisdom of the internets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Don't play this one.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Irem Corp."></category><category term="1985"></category><category term="American football"></category><category term="NES"></category></entry><entry><title>First Impressions: 1942</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1942.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-19T21:22:44-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2006-09-24:too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1942.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The famous vertical scrolling shooter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1942 title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1942_01.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not too bad. You control the plane, which moves pretty smoothly, and shoot the enemies. A rather basic idea, but workable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1942 title screen" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/images/1942_04.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this one just doesn't measure up to its sequel, 1943. I can't show it in a screenshot, but the sound was annoying--there was a beeping sort of sound going on while playing. The graphics, too, aren't as good as in 1943.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict: Play &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/too-much-free-time/first-impressions-1943-the-battle-of-midway.html"&gt;1943&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="1986"></category><category term="decent"></category><category term="NES"></category><category term="vertical scrolling shooter"></category><category term="Capcom"></category><category term="World War 2"></category></entry></feed>